<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the eloquence of these times, particularly of the barr and pulpit</title>
            <title>Reflexions sur l'eloquence de l'usage de ce temps. English</title>
            <author>Rapin, René, 1621-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12681404</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12681404</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 367:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the eloquence of these times, particularly of the barr and pulpit</title>
                  <title>Reflexions sur l'eloquence de l'usage de ce temps. English</title>
                  <author>Rapin, René, 1621-1687.</author>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Preston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Reflexions sur l'eloquence de l'usage de ce temps.</note>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: N.N.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to René Rapin. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oratory --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LICENSED <hi>Roger L' Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Decemb. 13. 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Eloquence OF THESE TIMES; Particularly of the BARR AND PULPIT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Preſton</hi> in Turn-ſtile Alley in <hi>Holborn,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO HIS Ingenious Friend <hi>T.B.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Loquence is ſo natural to perſons of your Houſe, that it is difficult to form any Ideas, but what you have already conceived; or to write any thing upon this glorious Subject, that you have not perfectly conſidered. All the world knows, that it was this Eloquence, joyned with a great Capacity, with a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity yet more great, and with all thoſe Vertues which <hi>Quintilian</hi> gives for its companions, which hath advanced your Father to the firſt preferments in the Church, and
<pb facs="tcp:65667:3"/>who yet attracts the admiration of of this renowned Kingdom. The chiefeſt glory that you have acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in purſuing ſuch noble paths, you have obtained from Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: It is to her that you owe thoſe great praiſes, that you have merited in your firſt ſally into the World. For this cauſe, Sir, the Reflections that I preſent you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long moſt juſtly to your ſelf; do you protect them, Sir, and it will render them more acceptable to thoſe who read them: For who can refuſe to read, or give their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation to what appears authorized by a name ſo auſpitious to Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as yours is?</p>
            <p>How oft, Sir, have I admir'd that ſolid Spirit, that excellent Judgment, that vaſt and illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted underſtanding, which you have in all things, and in which you are ſo very much diſtinguiſh'd from all thoſe that are conſiderable, upon
<pb facs="tcp:65667:3"/>the account of their vertue and great qualities? But as you aſpire not to any other reputation, but what flows, mixt with pleaſure, from an honourable diſcharge of your ſacred Function, I forbear to make a further diſcovery of what all the world obſerves in you, &amp; which all your modeſty cannot conceal: Yet how would the Publick accuſe me, if out of fear of wounding your modeſty, I ſhould neglect to ſpeak of that unexampled moderation which you have witneſſed in the flower of your Age, in renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all things, to apply your ſelf only to copy, even to the leaſt Tracts, from that admirable Model which you have perpetually before your eyes.</p>
            <p>It is there Sir, that you find an inexhauſtible fountain of bounty, of Knowledge, and of Piety, which are not to be met elſewhere. How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely above others are you ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb facs="tcp:65667:4"/>capable of all theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences by a Study ſuch as that is, and by an imitation of ſuch a Father? O what a happineſs is it, to have a domeſtick example, which alone includes all others!</p>
            <p>It is not Fortune alone that diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes theſe advantages; there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired vertue, which muſt be as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalized in a Family to merit theſe favours of Heaven. I have ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too much for a man that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not to be known: For it is not enough to conceal my name, but I ſhould alſo have conceal'd my Zeal, and contented my ſelf that you know who I am, and with what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I am, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very humble and obedient Servant. N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:4"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Eloquence which rendred the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of it ſo illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the happy age of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and in that of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Predeceſſors Has now loſt all its wonted Charms, and natural Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The nobleneſs of its end, and dignity of its uſe, is ſo little preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in this vain and voluptuous Age, that it is no wonder to ſee it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into a thing meerly ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial. We labour in the compoſition of Perfumes, and our cares are only
<pb facs="tcp:65667:5"/>ſcrupulous in the diſpoſition of Words, and an arrangment of Sentences, with a beautiful variety of Periods; we commonly hunt after gliſtring Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, and making choice of expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which go to the pomp and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Language, even ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the contempt and ruine of Piety, whilſt we neglect, out of a ſloathful impatience, what goes to the eſſence of it. True Eloquence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in the number of Syllables, nor in a muſical ordering of Dactyles or Sponds to make up harmony. Of which kind was that Oration of <hi>Ovid,</hi> which <hi>Seneca</hi> calls <hi>ſolutum Carmen.</hi> Alas, how miſerably do they miſtake; who make it conſiſt in a few fugitive words. True Eloquence is a thing that ſurvives in the most ingrateful Memories, and makes its paſſage into the moſt ſecret parts of Man, deſcends to the bottom of his heart, and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces even to the Center of the ſoul: It is above the ſcrupulous Precepts of
<pb facs="tcp:65667:5"/>
               <hi>Grammarians. Priſcian</hi> has no longer any Juriſdiction over us; nor are his Precepts of more force to us than the Edicts of the Great <hi>Mogul.</hi> The Compilators of common places, the Copiers of others Rhetoricks, or the Tranſlators of ſome Chapters of <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian,</hi> are not of the number of thoſe who do ſucceſsfully attach or captivate the Soul; they may have their Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and be ſatisfied with their applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but yet all their victories are only in Picture, their triumphs in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, and all their falſe miracles but a ſhadow. The world is ſo far become reaſonable, as that pedantry has loſt its credit, even in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities. Their travel is to be pittied, who are buſied in the gathering and tying toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Flowers, and decking their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations in affected Ornaments, which only ſurprize the Ignorant and the Vulgar. True Eloquence has the mean of an Amazon, rather than of a Wanton; She is not ſo curious of her
<pb facs="tcp:65667:6"/>Ornaments, as of her Armes, and had rather gain the ſoul by an entire victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than debauch it for a few hours by a light ſatisfaction; all her charms are the charms of a Majeſtick Beauty, which only triumphs over great Souls, and dazle not the Imprudent by a borrowed and affected luſtre. It muſt well conſided, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the knowledge of all Sciences, an Orator muſt be acquainted with all the different avenues to the ſeat of Reaſon; he muſt perfectly know the ſtrength and weakneſs of humane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and thoſe parts of the ſoul that are moſt pregnable. I have often bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with indignation at the reading of ſome of our Late Writers; ſo much are alſo their ſtiles vitiated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved: and to ſee ſo few Imitators of that vigorous and majeſtick ſtile of our illuſtrious <hi>Bacon,</hi> which was the legitimate off-ſpring of his fine pregnant and powerful Imagination. As on the Stage, Farce has ſupplanted
<pb facs="tcp:65667:6"/>Comoedy, ſo in the Preſs the laſcivious and burleſque hath uſurp'd upon the grave and modeſt. And what is moſt deplorable, we have ſeen the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it ſelf debaſed by an impudent and ambitious Jargon; and even thoſe Authors which paſs for the moſt poliſhed, the moſt elaborate Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, are but <hi>nugas canoras,</hi> Six words are oftentimes cramed with twelve figures, and all their Sentences pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous and magnificent; but that Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence is ſo far removed from ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Majeſty of an Oratory ſtile, that the moſt raſh and prodigal Poeſie has nothing more licentious. The moſt of our young Orators, as well as Poets, are diſtempered by this wild and extravagant fury. In others we find an inequality, which renders their diſcourſes monſtrous; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are elevated with a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation approaching to fury; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſometimes depreſſed ſo low, that their ſtiles become flat and diſtaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb facs="tcp:65667:7"/>whereas it ought to be continued in a conſtant equality and ſweetneſs. <hi>Non eſt formoſa cujus crus lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut brachium, ſed illa cujus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa facies admirationem ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis partibus abſtulit.</hi> The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, Sir,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> are not wholly exempt from failings; their Eloquence is properly Pagan, which proceeds from the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of certain Authors, which has ſo imbued their minds with their Ideas, that they cannot forbear them in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the moſt Religious; how many thinking it better to ſay the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Perſwaſion</hi> than the <hi>Chriſtian Faith, &amp;c.</hi> Know Reader, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what I have ſaid, that I am ſo far from deſpiſing or underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing Elocution, that I praiſe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire it in whomſoever I find it; and I am as much in love with elegant words and noble expreſſions, which may adorn our Language, as any are: But yet, with <hi>Quintilian,</hi> I would have them ſerve to unfold a
<pb facs="tcp:65667:7"/>ſence yet more conſiderable. <hi>Curam ego verborum, rerum volo eſſe ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citudinem;</hi> A too great care of words, and their diſpoſition is equally blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, with a too great neglect. I am very ſenſible, that he who appears in Print, let the cauſe, as to himſelf, be never ſo good, profitable, or commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, expoſes himſelf to cenſure; yet I cannot forbear to urge the general importance of the Subject in excuſe of my pains. I know it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable in a time when our own Clergy are ſtill wreſtling with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that have been lately caſt upon them upon this account. Yet I muſt needs ſay, that had the ſtile of that Author been more modeſt and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he might have eſcaped the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of being ſeen in the Preſs the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time leſs to his advantage. Inſtructions are entertained with effect, when they are not too perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally addreſt: We may with civility glance at, but cannot, without rudeneſs
<pb facs="tcp:65667:8"/>and ill manners, ſtare upon the faults or imperfections of any man: And I think every man ought to be offended with himſelf, who violates that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious reſpect which they owe to the Church and Churchmen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PPage 6. Line 12. <hi>for fine active Spirits,</hi> read <hi>fine and active Spirits:</hi> and l. 15. f. <hi>this</hi> r. <hi>it is.</hi> P. 13. l. 15. f. <hi>as a skilful Painter knows,</hi> r. <hi>as a skilful Painter who knows.</hi> P. 14. l. 20. f. <hi>that the extremity and heat,</hi> r. <hi>that in theſe extremities the beat.</hi> P. 15. l. the laſt. f. <hi>Eſcheres</hi> r. <hi>Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> P. 24. l. 16. f. <hi>his Spirit</hi> r. <hi>our Spirit.</hi> P. 63. l. 23. f. <hi>dicerenter</hi> r. <hi>dicerentur.</hi> P. 80. l. 17. f. <hi>amongſt us</hi> r. <hi>among them.</hi> P. 88. l. 4. f. <hi>ſome tincture</hi> r. <hi>ſome tin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>ure of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi> P. 116. l. 19. f. <hi>pains</hi> r. <hi>pain.</hi> P. 131. f. <hi>minds</hi> r. <hi>means.</hi> l. 14.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65667:8"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Eloquence OF THESE TIMES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough true Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence hath a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er more abſolute than Authority, or Violence, to which we do not uſually ſubmit our ſelves more than in Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony and with conſtraint; yet its powers are ſubject to revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65667:9"/>and declinations, as all other things are: For we have much pain in theſe times to find any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of that Empire which it exerciſed upon the Spirits of men, and whereof there appear'd ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glorious marks in thoſe Ages and States where ſhe hath rul'd. We muſt not now expect ſuch miracles of Elocution, nor ſuch excellent works of Diſcourſe, as have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved birth in <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> when Eloquence was there the Miſtreſs univerſally ador'd.</p>
            <p>Let us not boaſt our ſelves upon the pretended Glory of our Age, which we prefer to all others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due deliberation; for at this day, who is the Orator that can be Maſter of the reſolution of thoſe to whom he ſpeaks, and force them to diveſt their pre-occupations, and renounce their Sentiments? We have heretofore ſeen Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in a ſhort moment reſtore a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65667:9"/>Calm in the moſt violent agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a people moved and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous: We have ſeen it in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed deliberations of a tumultuous Aſſembly, to make impreſſions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoped for upon their Spirits, and to appeaſe their Seditions by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the moſt fearful with Courage, and diſarming the inſolent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted, and conſtraining both to follow blindly her Counſels: We have ſeen her alſo in Arms, in the ſhape of <hi>Pallas,</hi> fly from Rank to Rank, and reſtore heart to fainting and flying Souldiers; and in fine, to triumph amidſt the Armies of thoſe whom ſhe hath vanquiſh'd by her Reaſons.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak truly, at the preſent, we have only remaining a vain Phantome of that victorious Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which we now poſſeſs not but in <hi>Idaea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ingenii ipſius lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia. <hi>Cic. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Let us examine then from whence comes this Diſorder in a time wherein we have ſo much Spirit.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65667:10"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARiſtotle, Cicero, Quintilian,</hi> and <hi>Longinus,</hi> which have left us Treatiſes of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> the moſt accompliſh'd of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, remark that that Eloquence which they had ſeen ſometimes in <hi>Athens</hi> and in <hi>Rome,</hi> before that theſe Republicks had loſt their liberty, could not rule then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a People free and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: She is a fierce and haughty Miſtriſs, who cannot be made ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Vaſſalage or Flattery: She ſeems to bear in her Character that of a Monarchy, which cannot ſubmit without deſtroying it ſelf: And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> obſerves that ſhe had not any ſucceſs in <hi>Cicily,</hi> during that the Tyrants were their Maſters, when all other Arts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued there and flouriſhed. This was the opinion of theſe great men,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65667:10"/>who were very able to judge of the truth, though they licenſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſpeak ſomthing in favour of the Government wherein they had been advanced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>As the Honours that <hi>Greece</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to Eloquence, made it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable amongſt other Nations, and the ſucceſs it had at <hi>Rome</hi> was by the great rewards which were propoſed; ſo her Credit ceaſed there, when her Recompences were taken away. We muſt not then be aſtoniſhed, (the Fruit which we gain from this Art, being now ſo diſproportionate to the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and application that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands) if we find ſo few Orators ſo couragious as to ſuſtain the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigue,<note place="margin">Sibi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſerunt neminem ſine elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiae, aut aſſequi poſſe in Civitate, aut tueri conſpicuum &amp; emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentem locum: <hi>De cauſ. corrup. Eloq.</hi>
                  </note> eſpecially when it is not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65667:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>by any hopes which ſmile either on their Intereſt or Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Eloquence was the means to attain to the greateſt Honours in thoſe Eſtates in which ſhe had Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; but in theſe times there is little or nothing to be obtained by the ſame way: This alone is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to extinguiſh that generous ardeur and ſtudy which is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Eloquence, and to rebate the moſt fine active Spirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>That greatneſs of Genius which Eloquence requires, and which we ſearch after, is now no more to be found: This is a gift of Heaven, and a work of many Ages; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a happy birth for the pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, the ſole Aſſembly of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Qualities requir'd to ſucceed in this Art of Speech, is extreamly rare; there is required an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65667:11"/>elevation of Spirit, a great judgment formed by a natural ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity, to which the uſage of the world, and a profound knowledge of Letters, muſt give perfection: There is alſo required a vaſt Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and an extended Imagination, an eaſie Comprehenſion, a Voice clear and diſtinct, a Viſage that hath nothing of forbidding, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation fine and animated, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an Air of Authority; and many other Qualities, which being uſually incompatible of themſelves, are very difficultly found all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſembled:<note place="margin">Cernimus vix ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aetati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus binos Oratores laudabiles extitiſſe. <hi>De Orat.</hi>
                  </note> 'Tis this that gave cauſe to <hi>Cicero</hi> to complain, in his time, when Eloquence was ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, that he could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great trouble find in that Age, two Orators that merited eſteem; yet this is no reaſon but that they may be found no was well as at other times; for Nature is as liberal of her gifts in theſe laſt times, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65667:12"/>ſhe was in the firſt; but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily we have not ſo much light, to know in our ſelves thoſe qualities, when they are there; or ſufficient care or application to cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate them; ſo that they are there, as if they were not at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>Beſides this natural diſpoſition, there is required to be eloquent, a great capacity, and a great appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Theſe were the three things which rendred the Eloquence of <hi>Brutus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Erat in <hi>Bruto</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris. <hi>De clar. Orat.</hi>
                  </note> which <hi>Cicero</hi> praiſed ſo much, ſo very accompliſh'd: There muſt be a great Attachment to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and an extraordinary diligence at the Cabinet to repleniſh the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with knowledges neceſſary to Eloquence. It is good to draw from the Sources, to ſtudy to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65667:12"/>bottom the Ancients, principally thoſe which are original; and in fine, to make a Subject of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Meditation the Rhetorick of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who hath taken the care to expoſe ſo exactly all the particular motions of mans heart. The Orator ought to make the chief end of his Study to move the Souls of his Auditors by the move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Affections, which are the true reſorts of this Machine, which is ſo difficult to enflame, when we beſtow no time in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of them.</p>
               <p>Without this knowledge an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator is in a condition to determine nothing, nor to obtain the attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an Oracle, which he muſt ordinarily be eſteemed; nor can his ſpirit be capable of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſonable production, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the opinion of the judicious Critick, <hi>Neque concipere, neque edere partum mens poteſt, niſi ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65667:13"/>flumine literarum undata.</hi> By what means can he enlighten o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if he himſelf be not enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? or how can he perſwade, if himſelf be not perſwaded? And who is there now who can ſuſtain the travel of a ſtudy ſo <hi>opiniaſtre,</hi> and of a perſeverance ſo great, as muſt be that of the Orator, who muſt be ignorant of nothing?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>The true Eloquence being ſo difficult to acquire, we think at leaſt to recompenſe it by the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of a falſe Eloquence, which had its firſt courſe amongſt the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latines,</hi> in the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of their Republicks, which never had any ſubſiſtence or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment than in the ſervitude of theſe Nations. The <hi>Sophiſts,</hi> whoſe Lives <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> and <hi>Eunapius</hi> have deſcrib'd, eſtabliſh'd in their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65667:13"/>publick places, this falſe eloquence, which gives all to the exteriour part by aiery and wandring Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and hath no other tendency, than to amuſe the people: but as this Eloquence has nothing of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, the Figures themſelves and the Ornaments ſerve only to render it more weak.</p>
               <p>All its Movements are falſe; it touches not at all the heart, nor enters in any manner into the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; all that it gives, is a pleaſure ſuperficial, and is no more than a ſimple paſtime for the fooliſh and idle. But as it is eaſie to miſtake univerſally the falſe for the true; for the former quickly offers it ſelf to the Spirit; but the latter is not found than with ſtudy and with care: the firſt is immenſe by the multiplicity of its appearances, which ſerve to diſguiſe it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the other has none, and conſiſts in ſome kind in a point indiviſible:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65667:14"/>We ought not to be aſtoniſhed if we take Appearance for Truth in Eloquence, as in other things; but when we arrive to true diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we find that there is little of true Eloquence or perfect Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and that the moſt part of thoſe which ſpeak in publick, are no other than pure Declamators.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>We exerciſe not our ſelves to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this Eloquence in the way that is moſt ordinary, and ſure to ſucceed in the purſuit, that is, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent exerciſe in compoſition,<note place="margin">Nulla res ad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum proficit quantum ſcriptio. <hi>Cic.</hi> fu <hi>Brut.</hi>
                  </note> to which we muſt apply our ſelves with no little aſſiduity to acquire a habitude; for nothing is equal to the advantage we receive by it: It was by this way that <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> are come to that degree of perfection which every one knows; and without ſpeaking of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65667:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>firſt who ſpent ſo many years in that acqueſt;<note place="margin">Caput eſt quod mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me faci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus; eſt enim mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni laboris quod fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gimus quam plurimum ſcribere, <hi>De Orat.</hi>
                  </note> no perſon is ignorant that the latter employ'd all his leiſure which his Affairs allow'd him, to exerciſe himſelf to ſpeak well, by this frequent uſe of Compoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>We ſtudy not to ſpeak things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, nor to make our Images and Portraicts equal; we ſpeak uſually too much or too little; the Mean that we muſt hold, is known to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few perſons, for that it is almoſt imperceptible; to attain which Knowledge, we have but very few Rules. And as a skilful Painter knows how to diſtinguiſh Paſſions in different Subjects wherein he is to expreſs them; he does not make the joy of a Prince like that of a <hi>Valet,</hi> nor the fiercneſs of a common
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65667:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Souldier equal to that of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. There are alſo in the motions of the Soul different degrees, which the Orator ought to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, to avoid the confuſion of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; Which are not well compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended or underſtood but by thoſe who are perfect Maſters of the Art. The Ignorance of this Principle, ſo little practiſed, occaſions the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo many falſe pictures of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.<note place="margin">In omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus rebus videndum quatenus; etſi enim ſuus cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> modus eſt, tamen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus offen dit nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quam parum. <hi>De clar. Or at.</hi>
                  </note> It is important in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Idea's which preſent themſelves to the Fancy, to make a juſt choice, and to avoid taking the falſe for the true; this demands an exact diſcernment, a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and an exquiſite under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; we ought above all, to make a reflection, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and heat of our Fancy may not tranſport us, and <hi>the too much</hi> ſhocks more than the <hi>too little.</hi> This is that which the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator reproves ſo many times in his books
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65667:15"/>of Rhetorick: For the too much is alwayes a mark that we are tranſported beyond our ſelves, which is a great fault; but the too little may ſeem a mark of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Reſerve, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a Virtue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>We think it not enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow our Cares in the ſtudy of our natural diſpoſition, to follow its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, without committing ſome conſtraint in affecting Manners, which becomes us not, and in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing through violent ſtudies, wherewith we become overbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened; or in fine, in impoſing an air of Greatneſs, or of more Art than we are able to ſuſtain; this began (as <hi>Cicero</hi> notes) firſt to make Eloquence degenerate from that Grandeur which it had in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> under <hi>Pericles, Lyſias, Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65667:16"/>and <hi>Demoſthenes;</hi> for that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius Phalerius</hi> affected more of Art than his Genius could bear.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phalereus</hi> non tam armis, quam Palaeſtra inſlitutus, <hi>Cicero in Brut.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>The Pronunciation, which is one of the moſt important parts of Eloquence, is yet one of the moſt neglected: It renders Eloquence ſenſible to the people by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the exteriour part, and which hath the Art to impoſe by the appearances, when it wants the power to touch by its effects. If its virtue be ſo great, as to make impreſſion in Subjects feigned and ſuppoſed, as it doth upon a Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a Comedy, what can ſhe not do, when things true are her ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject? But this admirable Art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes unprofitable to thoſe which ſpeak in publick, becauſe of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65667:16"/>little care they have to uſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it; 'tis true, he muſt have much of the natural in him, who ſucceeds well in this Art; but where he wants that, application may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. The Eloquence of <hi>Demoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes</hi> became admirable by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, though he had not any natural diſpoſition; and he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged for his ſucceſs, to the pains that he took to obtain it: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſoon weary of theſe conſtraints, we cannot reſolve to give our ſelves the pain that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to form our ſelves to this exeroiſe whereby we loſe that great advantage that the pronunciation gives to an Orator, by giving a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain agreement to his perſon, and by the paſſionate expreſſions which it inſpires even into his Eyes and Viſage: Alſo we may truly ſay, that nothing fruſtrates more the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary effects of Eloquence than the little care we have of the exterior
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65667:17"/>part, whoſe faults become ſo much more ſenſible, as they are above, in delicacy, the other pleaſures we receive from Eloquence; which being an Art to pleaſe by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which it makes, hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more oppoſed to it, than that which is violent and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable in the action.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>Thoſe which make profeſſion to ſpeak in publick, are not ſo careful to put in uſe their Logick, either by a pure negligence to inſtruct themſelves in it, or by a natural debility to practiſe it; or in fine, by a very blameable regret they have to put themſelves in pain of a little Meditation, in which the Diſcourſes of Ceremony, or of Intereſts of State, with thoſe of Religion, have not any part; and thoſe which are purely for pomp and preparation,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65667:17"/>are ordinarily thoſe wherein Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick finds its ſelf moſt defective; for that they are too wandring, or too abſtract for the general matters whereof they treat. Logick is the firſt Rule of Diſcourſe, and the univerſal Organ of Speech; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe without this Inſtrument, 'tis but to beat the Air, and make a noiſe; we canot ſay any thing that's judicious, or ſupportable, without it. How oft do we abandon it? and when we put it into uſe, how many extravagances do we commit, either by the confuſion of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions wherewith we perplex it; or in fine, by the <hi>Idea</hi> we form of falſe Reaſonings, to ſupply the want of the true Reaſon, which cannot inhabit but in a Spirit fine and penetrating: The rareneſs of ſuch a Character is the reaſon that we find Eloquence ſo defective in the moſt part of thoſe which make profeſſion of it; for that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65667:18"/>on which they eſtabliſh it, are either too myſterious, or too common, or altogether falſe and Chimaerical; and if we examine things well, we ſhall find that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in the uſage of Eloquence in this age, there is no defect ſo eſſential as that of Reaſoning, to which we have no great care to form our ſelves. This is not ſo much obtained by the ſtudy of Logick, which we learn at the Colledge; as by the reading <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, and by the frequent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce we muſt have with good Books, the reading whereof im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints upon the ſpirit a juſtneſs of apprehenſion, which cannot be acquired without it. A right judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſometimes a Gift which comes purely from Nature; but when we have it not, we muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to find it in Books, whereof we muſt be careful to make a good choice; for we may meet with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65667:18"/>ſome Books, which, inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying, may quite deſtroy our judgments: We muſt therefore take counſel of the moſt knowing perſons, upon what we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to underſtand our ſelves. The neglect of this, is the reaſon why ſo few perſons are capable, and young men yet more than others; for that their experience and the uſage of things have not yet form'd their Spirit: But though the want of Logick be the moſt ordinary defect of thoſe that ſpeak in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, yet it is a thing whereof there alwayes appears the leaſt want; for none but men of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſpirits, whereof there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the feweſt, are capable of that knowledge; not but that the people perceive very well the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural order of Diſcourſe, and all that there is of Logick in it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing it; but their Light reaches not ſo far to ſee what is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65667:19"/>falſe in his Reaſonings, or defectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the order and purſuit of his Deſign: Upon which we may make three Orders of Spirits, the firſt, of thoſe which attend only to the Words, to judge of their Beauty; the ſecond, of thoſe which go further, and who judge of the Thoughts: the third, of thoſe which go even to judge even of the whole Deſign, Order and Proportion of the Parts; which laſt is not known but by the moſt intelligent. There are ſome Orators who leave not their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors liberty to examine the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of their Diſcourſe, by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Charm of Words and of Thoughts, wherewith they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize them: There are ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which quite blind us by the agreeable manner of expreſſing things. I have known a perſon of this ſort, who alwayes pleas'd, though his Diſcourſe was very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65667:19"/>correct, either in the Order or Reaſoning: but after all, he pleas'd none but Women and the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; the more underſtanding e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd him not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>When we apply our ſelves to the ſtudy of Eloquence, we are accuſtomed to miſtake, by the falſe meaſures we take of it, or of its Subject, or of thoſe to whom we addreſs our ſelves. For an Orator who hath a great elevation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, many times takes too great a pleaſure in purſuing his own Fancy, without giving any care to proportion his Diſcourſe to the Subject, or to meaſure the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe to whom he ſpeaks; it is much more eaſie to abandon our ſelves to the impetuoſity of our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, than to regulate our ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Circumſtances of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65667:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>the things we ſpeak of; for one is the effect of Imagination, the other the effect of Judgment, which is a Gift more rare. Alſo it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel if thoſe that ſpeak in publick, are ſo ſubject to this Diſorder, out of which ſpring ſo many Indecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and choquant Diſproportions which are jumbled together in our ordinary diſcourſes which are made publick; as the aſſuming of an air of greatneſs in the moſt trivial af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and affecting grand expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the moſt petty Subjects; making oſtentation of the beauty of his Spirit to the people, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a groſs and ſtupid Auditory, and being ardent and pathetick in Subjects which deſerve it not. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence ceaſes to be true,<note place="margin">Refert cognoſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re qui ſunt audienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um mores, quae publica recepta perſuaſio. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> when it hath no proportion with the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of thoſe to whom it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65667:20"/>The diverſity of Ages,<note place="margin">Ut guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator ad incurſus tempeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſie agenti ad varieta tem cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ratio mutanda. <hi>Quintil.</hi> l. 10, cap. 7.</note> Sexes and Conditions, and of Lights acquired or natural, ought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Orator in different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to proportion it to the Spirits of theſe different eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>It muſt be known in general to diſtinguiſh the divers Characters of Eloquence, for to ſerve himſelf according to the neceſſity of the Subject whereof we treat, leſt we fall into confuſion. And we muſt be eſpecially careful of this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe nothing is capable to ſucceed in this Art out of its place. The grand Air of Eloquence ought to be in great places, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Aſſemblies, where we find a general concourſe: For we muſt ſpeak to perſons of great quality in that kind of Diſcourſe which hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65667:21"/>moſt of eſteem, extention and grandeur of expreſſion. This Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter ought to be uſed in the moſt elevated Subjects, and in the moſt important matters; as it ought to be ſimple,<note place="margin">Tenues cauſae tenue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendifilum requirunt. <hi>Orat.</hi> Oratio poſcitur auſtera, ſi accuſes; fuſa, ſi laudes. <hi>Quintil.</hi> l. 9. c. 4. Loquendi accurata, &amp; ſine moleſtia diligens Elegantia. <hi>Cic.</hi> in <hi>Brut.</hi>
                  </note> natural, and without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of expreſſion in leſſer Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Praiſes demand a Stile ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated and diffuſed; Accuſations ſerious and auſtere; in fine, Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence hath arrived to its utmoſt perfection, when it knows to adapt words proportionate to things, and to conſerve the care to unfold her ſelf without difficulty or ſcruple. There remains two things eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be avoided, the cold Stile, and the Boyiſh; for the firſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Diſcourſe dry and inſipid, by the faint languor and lowneſs of its expreſſion; the ſecond ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it diſtaſtful and tedious by its
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65667:21"/>affected amplifications, wherewith they weary the patience of the Auditor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>Thought that <hi>Longin.</hi> confounds in ſome faſhion the cold Stile, and Boyiſh, whereof I have ſpoken we may alwayes diſtinguiſh them in this manner; in the affectation of a cold Stile, we uſe great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Subjects which demand little; and in the Boyiſh, we uſe little and low expreſſions in things that demand great: But our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is become ſo modeſt, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and ſcrupulous, that it rejects all expreſſions too ſtrong and gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering, Metaphors too hardy, and the too frequent points in a cold ſtile, as it does in the Boyiſh, the little exultations in ſerious matters, and the too languiſhing amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in thoſe places of diſcourſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65667:22"/>which ought to be ſerious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 14.</head>
               <p>It is impoſſible to be happy in an elevated Stile, when we are not entirely perſwaded that it is formed of the things themſelves which we have to ſpeak, of the great images which we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and of the elevation of our Genius more than that of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the vain ſplendor of words, or that train of ſtudied Periphraſes. This is that which in Diſcourſe, in ſome manner, is like that load of Fleſh in the Body of man, which ſerves only to charge &amp; imbarraſs it with an unprofitable weight; for when this elevated Stile is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, it degenerates into a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter low and reptile; for it cannot ſuſtain it ſelf. <hi>Pindar</hi> and <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> elevated themſelves ſo high by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65667:22"/>the grandeur of their expreſſion, that they could not, without much pain, purſue it. And when they could not bear up that elevation, which is not natural; for that it is not alwayes in the things they ſpeak of; they ſometimes abaſe themſelves even to a contempt, and become not knowabl even to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. This is a fault not to be pardoned; for there is a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of appearing great without being ſo, and a deſire to elevate themſelves without being able to ſuſtain themſelves in that height. The Secret is to ſtudy how to think of things worthily,<note place="margin">Oratio ſententiis debet eſſe ornatior<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis. <hi>Fab.</hi>
                  </note> and ſerve our ſelves of no other words than of thoſe which are capable to anſwer to the dignity of the Subject whereof we ſpeak.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65667:23"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 15.</head>
               <p>As the great defect of the wiſer ſort of men is the negligence they have to meaſure themſelves upon the capacity of the Subject, or their Auditory. That of the leſſer Genius's is a too ſcrupulous care, and a too affected Diligence to attach themſelves more than is required, to finiſh in particular cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain parts of the Diſcourſe they have enterprized, &amp; to which they have ſome peculiar affection. This is a pure effect of their little judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to tie themſelves to one part of a Deſign; for they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor ſo happy as to form a Deſign all entire. Theſe narrow Spirits ſuffer themſelves to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd into a falſe Principle, which they would authorize by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Tyrius Maximus,</hi> who pretends that Art hath alwayes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65667:23"/>ſomething more perfect than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and that we cannot find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny natural Beauty that can be ſo perfect as ſome of their artificial Statues. I pretend not to enter into a Diſcuſſion of that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with this Philoſopher: But Eloquence being the true Art to pleaſe, which ſhe cannot do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an imitation of Nature, that Maxime of thoſe little Spirits which give ſo much to Art, is not a very ſure mean to perſwade. I pretend not only that Rule is falſe, but that their too Boyiſh Attachment to Precepts which they have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their youth, hath form'd in them a very vicious Idaea of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: We need not then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the <hi>Agamemnon</hi> of <hi>Petronus,</hi> to comprehend the ridiculouſneſs of that Eloquence which hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of natural in it; for that it faſtens it ſelf too much upon the exterior Ornaments, which they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65667:24"/>would have to paſs for that which is moſt eſſential. The true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Eloquence is a good Judgment, which as it is the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity moſt neceſſary to ſpeak in publick, ſo it is the moſt rare; we need not be aſtoniſhed that we find ſo few perfect Orators, ſince a perfect Orator cannot be form'd but in an Age happy, and in a people of good Guſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 16.</head>
               <p>The Soveraign Art of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence conſiſteth in a ſcrupulous attention to Nature, as to its true Model, and firſt Original, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have ſo little knowledge, by reaſon of the little care we take to purſue the Tracts, and to obſerve the conduct; we muſt ſtudy then to know well this great Model, and to examine all its Reſorts by a profound ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65667:24"/>of Philoſophy, and a long ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of natural things; for ſo often as we depart from Nature we fall into errour and miſtake; the heat of our moſt paſſionate moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is but a falſe heat; the moſt dazling ſplendour of her Figures are but a falſe and deceitful blaze; and the greateſt of her Reaſons hath nothing real, and is no other than a ſophiſtical Declamation and pure Illuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 17.</head>
               <p>We find very little of conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Diſcourſes of the moſt of our publick Orators, becauſe they apply not themſelves to ſtudy the Rules of Speech. Thoſe which have a genius for Eloquence find it a trouble to abaſe themſelves to thoſe little ſcrupulous cares which are neceſſary to ſucceed well; the natural elevation of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65667:25"/>their ſpirit cannot be ſubjected to thoſe circumſpections; and thoſe that have not that genius, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to fall into the fault of affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſupply by words that which they want of light to underſtand things well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>The moſt ordinary ſource of thoſe defects which we meet with in the expreſſion, which is ſo eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Eloquence, comes from the natural defects of the imagination. The expreſſion falls into a Lux and into ſuperfluity, when the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination is too quick and ardent; ſhe falls into galimatia's and into obſcurity, when the Imagination is too abundant and too profuſe: In fine, it falls into a faint langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and inſipidneſs, when the Imagination is too cold, too heavy and enveloped.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65667:25"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 19.</head>
               <p>We ſcarce ever ſtudy that juſt temperament which is of ſo much uſe in the mixing in our Diſcourſe, Reaſon with Authority, Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Similitude with Example and Induction. In the uſage it ſelf which we make of this great Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of perſwaſion, we apply not our ſelves with any care to arrange our reaſons in ſuch a manner, as that the one may ſuſtain the other by the order which we give them; for the ſtronger Reaſons ought to ſucceed the weak, and the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid to thoſe that are the leſs ſolid, to the end that the Diſcourſe may ſuſtain and elevate it ſelf the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it approaches to the period of its perfection. This is a thing of ſuch Importance, that the only neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this obſervation renders ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the reaſonings which are very
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65667:26"/>ſtrong and ſolid, little effective, for that they weaken themſelves when the proportion of the reaſons is not obſerved. This proportion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the not urging of any thing that may appear weak, when we have ſaid any thing more perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive: For the latter Reaſons make the moſt laſting impreſſion in the ſpirit, and ought therefore, as I have ſaid before, to be the moſt ſtrong. Beſides the mannagement of the Reaſons, which ought to be placed in their natural order, and ought not to be confounded, they muſt alſo be orderly mannaged in the uſe which we make of Inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt we be expoſed to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate multiplication. Alſo our Orator muſt have that admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Art, which knows generouſly to retrench ſuperfluities in things as well as words, and to ſuppreſs too frequent Ornaments, without hearkning to the tranſport of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65667:26"/>Imagination, which by a natural inclination ſuffers it ſelf to be carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away to a vain ſplendour of Diſcourſe, which uſually hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſolid Eloquence, he cannot move with ſucceſs thoſe great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines of het Art, without theſe precautions, which are of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conſequence, for that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce things to their natural eſtate. But theſe Obſervations are but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom practic'd, becauſe they are but little known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 20.</head>
               <p>That Eloquence which touches not the ſpirit, and makes not its way to the heart, is not true Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, it is no more than a pure inſtruction, which ought not to be uſed but in the School. And all thoſe Beauties which ſmite the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without affecting the heart, are not true Beauties. That great Air
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65667:27"/>it ſelf which <hi>Longinus</hi> teaches, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects but little, when it doth not dazle nor aſtoniſh, as he avows himſelf, for that it enters not into the thoughts of thoſe to whom we ſpeak. All thoſe great expreſſions, without as great thoughts, are like thoſe great Ships that are not bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced, they float, and never ſail in ſafety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 21.</head>
               <p>That Eloquence in general which beſtowes too much care in the arrangment of words,<note place="margin">Cum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogat affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, et u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicunq: ais o lentatur veritas ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Quint. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 4. Non ad judiciorum certamen, ſed ad voluptatem aurium ſcripſerat <hi>Iſocrates.</hi> Cic Orat.</note> and of that outward ſplendour which gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the expreſſion, almoſt never ſucceeds. We are uſually diſpleas'd with all things which appear ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died and artificial. That great O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> which wrote, as it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65667:27"/>ſeems, only for pleaſure, was not fit for affairs, and had never ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Barr, for that he was too poliſh'd. This was the manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Sophiſts, upon whom <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> rallyes ſo pleaſantly in <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>'s <hi>Phaedra,</hi> and <hi>Longinus</hi> notes in the great artifice of <hi>Hiperides,</hi> who uſed to fill his Diſcourſe with too many Ornaments, and too many beauties. It is a great Art to know how to mannage theſe Ornaments, and to diſpoſe them in their due place, when neceſſity obliges to make uſe of them. The Artifice of Eloquence cannot have any effect, but againſt it ſelf, when it is too dazling, for thereby it becomes ſuſpected, and we regard it only as a Page which is gawdily dreſt,<note place="margin">Quae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt retia vitat av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </note> for no other end than to ſurprize. Beſides, that which ſtrikes the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and the ſenſe with too much ſplendor, wearies and oppreſſes. In fine, 'tis neceſſary that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65667:28"/>themſelves be not without beauty to bear thoſe great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which become ridiculous in little Subjects; for there is nothing more contrary to Art, than to adorn what merits it not: And 'tis not of the leaſt importance in this Art, to know what is to be neglected, and what is not. To be too expenſive in Ornaments, is but a vain and fruitleſs prodigality; for we often find, that which gliſters moſt in Diſcourſe is moſt uſually falſe. Thoſe ſtudied Figures, thoſe fine Antitheſies, and thoſe ſplendid E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithites, are not alwayes conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to good ſenſe. True Eloquence doth not dazle or ſurprize, but inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates by little and little into the ſpirit. The Reaſons that are moſt capable to move, are ordinarily the moſt common, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teacheth us.<note place="margin">Topic. 1.</note> And the moſt natural Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to which we are carried, by the ſole deſire we have to make
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65667:28"/>our ſelves underſtood, is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and the beſt. Thoſe Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which require much of ſpirit and ornament, as Panegyricks, and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Orations, contain little that's very ſolid, and generally owe their ſucceſs to the pronunciation: We may diſcover the truth when they come to the Preſs; which I adviſe thoſe that make them, not to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. When they want that heat of action which firſt gave them life, they make no longer any impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There are Images in Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as there is in painting, which ſomtime muſt be ſhown to the view ar a diſtance, and ſomtime near at hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 22.</head>
               <p>There is required in Eloquence leſs of Genius to invent things, than to place them in order: For that place which we muſt aſſign (to have them diſpos'd where they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65667:29"/>ought to be) will coſt more than the pains we are at in cogitation and invention; for every reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit may have reaſonable thoughts; but it is not ſo eaſie to give to our thoughts that grace which renders things agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and which makes them to be admir'd. This is it in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts Eloquence: I mean not that Eloquence of words which we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily know but too much, but the Eloquence of things, which we ſeldom well underſtand, and have little knowledg of; and the perfect attainment of which, we cannot hope than from an happy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We may know the price of this Art, by the great difference in the ſame things diverſified. This right diſpoſal of things ordinarily makes the beauty of an Oration; and though this Air be uſually the bounty of our Nature, yet we have means to acquire it, when Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65667:29"/>hath denyed it; as a frequent uſe of Compoſition under a good Maſter, or an intelligent friend, and a diligent commerce with ancient Authors; it is from them that we learn that juſtneſs which gives to the Spirit that agreeable variety, and which the ſpirit communicates to all its thoughts and Imaginations when we have a Genius for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 23.</head>
               <p>There is not, according to the ſentiment of <hi>Cicero,</hi> any true Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,<note place="margin">Eloquenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quae admiratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non habet nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamjudico. <hi>Cic in Brut.</hi>
                  </note> but that which doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract an admiration; and there is nothing more capable to render it admirable, according to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that great man, than the pictures that it makes of manners, and thoſe motions that it excites in thoſe divers paſſions which it toucheth. This cannot be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted without a perfect knowledg
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65667:30"/>of the heart of man, which ought to be the ſoveraign Science of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator. The Portraicts that he makes of manners cannot be falſe, if he know well the principal, which is the heart; and he will know without doubt, how to move with ſucceſs the moſt hidden Parts of the ſoul, that is to ſay, the Paſſions, by the ſame knowledg of the heart, which is the ſourſe. The little cares (that the moſt part of thoſe that ſpeak in publick have to know the depth of that abyſm which appears ſo difficult to deſcend) is the cauſe that we have ſo few ſucceſsful Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. For this cauſe thoſe who make profeſſion of Eloquence, ought to make very ſerious Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; for all being well conſidered, no man is properly eloquent, who knows not the heart of man, and all its intricate Maeanders, to expoſe them to the people.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65667:30"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 24.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quis ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norat elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiam deſciviſſe a veteri gloria, no inopia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, ſed deſidia juventutis parentum negligen tia, et inſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium.</note>The evil Education of Youth, cauſed by the extream luxury and delicateneſs of this Age, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of Parents, by the little experience of Maſters, and by the ignorance of the moſt part of thoſe with whom we converſe, is one of the moſt certain Cauſes that there is ſo little ſucceſs in this Art, it being one of the greateſt obſtacles to Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. We conduct our Youth through falſe and unequal paths, and through very unskilful me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, who being corrupted even in their principals, it is no wonder if their ſucceſs be ſo little happy, and their purfuits unprofitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 25.</head>
               <p>I do not affirm that there are not yet ſome ſparks of wit remaining,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65667:31"/>which eminently ſhine in ſome of the Orators of this Age, who ceaſe not to merit applauſe and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but becauſe Eloquence purely natural cannot atchieve any thing without the ſuccour of Art, as may be uſually obſerved either by the falſe principles which we aſſume, or the little application of thoſe who make profeſſion of it: it cannot ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to merit the general admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, by the marveilous effects which it would produce up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hearts if it were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
               <p>I have thus finiſhed the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may be made upon the uſe of the Eloquence of this Time, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in general; and upon that which may hinder its effects in thoſe occaſions which it hath to make appear its power over hearts. Thoſe that follow are Reflections upon the uſe of Eloquence in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65667:31"/>particular, and the two principal Species of it, The Eloquence of the <hi>Barr,</hi> and that of the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> wherein I have remarked the abuſe which may be committed in the one and in the other, and the means to ſucceed with moderate felicity in both.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:65667:32"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Eloquence OF THE BARR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Loquence in General may be reduced to two Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: Whereof one is occupied in Intereſts of State; The other in thoſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: alſo one is prophane, the other Sacred. The firſt hath a vaſter Cariere than we are able to think; ſhe is not bufied only to ſuſtain an Ordinance, nor to defend a Law; ſhe exerciſeth her ſelf in rhe Campaign, as well as in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65667:32"/>Cabinet; ſhe preſides over States, and is imploy'd in Councils of War; ſhe rules in the Camp, and hath the greateſt part in the Government and Miniſtry of Kingdomes. But becauſe ſhe is at all times more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in Cabinets, where we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not penetrate to come to the knowledg of her, where ſhe paſſeth for a Miſtery, and is no where ſo publick as at the Barr, I'le confine my ſelf to the ſtate which ſhe holds there, being the place where ſhe appears with moſt advantage.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>At the Barr we give no time to the ſtudy of Eloquence, but what we gave in the firſt ſtudies of our Youth, which are ordinarily too precipitate, too confuſed, or too ſuperficial. This renders us unable to form any juſt or reaſonable Idea of it. Beſides the great advantages
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65667:33"/>that the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> had by the force of their Genius, and by their great natural diſpoſitions they had to ſpeak, they made Eloquence their continual ſtudy during their lives they travel'd all the World to underſtand the moſt choyce Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this Art, they laid out a long time and ſtudy to form their ſpirits upon the great models which they went to ſeek out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries; they did not occupy themſelves as if they were to gain nothing by it; they placed their pleaſure, their hopes, their fortune, and all their ambition in the ſtudy of it, for ir was then able to elevate them to the greateſt Honours. But the young men of theſe Times (with a very indifferent genius's) believe that the reading of a Romance or a Comedy, is ſufficient to acquire all the Eloquence which is neceſſary to the Bar. We are not excited by the ſame hopes of Glory as the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65667:33"/>
                  <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> were, amongſt whom Eloquence attained ſo much ſplendour, becauſe it was the way that conducted to the higheſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, even to the Soveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>When all the Qualities requiſite to ſucceed in the Eloquence of the Barr concur in an Orator, with all the perſeverance of Application, and is encouraged in it by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Intereſt and Ambition; yet thoſe little condeſcentions to which he muſt ſubmit in a ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and exact uſage of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick, would be able to weary the ſpirit, and to take away the power to form an Idea according to Art and Nature; he muſt have a care to ſhun this default, and to prevent it by an anticipated ſtudy of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, where we muſt form the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65667:34"/>ſpirit, before we abandon the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination to the barbarous terms of the practick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>The Eloquence of the Barr is too much ſubjected to the divers Fantaſies of Language, which reign in this Age, according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent guſts which prevail, and corrupt it by taking away the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral beauties, &amp; in giving it falſe and adulterate. There was a tedious kind of Eloquence which had once the vogue amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> which conſiſted in a long and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing Diſcourſe: But this guſt changing with the Age, one more judicious ſucceeded. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it is true that the Eloquence of the barr demands a Manner diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and extended:<note place="margin">Subſelia grand io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem et ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niorem vocem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderant. <hi>Cic. in Brut.</hi>
                  </note> But that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barras of words to which theſe kind of Declamators uſually abandon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65667:34"/>themſelves, alwayes diſpleaſeth: We are not now taken with things ſo little real and ſolid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>Too great a care to appear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, exact and juſt in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is ſomtime very dangerous; it wearies both the attention of thoſe that ſpeak, and thoſe that hear. We ought to ſhun this fault, and muſt not alwayes be ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to ſpeak nothing but what is exact; it ſuffices to have a care to maintain a certain equality and evenneſs; for there is nothing more eſſential to him that ſpeaks, than to ſpeak according to his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, without force or conſtraint. Beſides, thoſe ſcrupulous Orators that ſpeak with ſo much circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, have nothing of great or elevated; the care they take to ſpeak things ſo correctly renders flat
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65667:35"/>their ſpirit; and they have not the power to move the heart by the greatneſs of their thoughts; they expoſe our Language by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and too much ſcruple, to looſe its force and abundance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too deſirous to preſerve its ſweetneſs and delicateneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>There is alſo another extremity to be avoided, which is a too great negligence, not only in the ornament of the words, but alſo in the right order and diſpoſal of things. Thoſe which have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy eſtabliſhed their Reputation, and which are accuſtom'd to a long uſage of the air of the Barr, are moſt ſubject to fall into this Errour; for when they arrive to above forty years of age, and to great imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they think then of nothing but of what is profitable and ſolid;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65667:35"/>they abandon the ornaments of Eloquence, for they have no time to ſpend in the thoughts of it: And the care of Intereſt ſurmounts that of Glory and Ambition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>There are ſome occaſions not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding where this negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is pardonable, and where the heat of a Diſcourſe, and the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſity of the Genius ſucceeds ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times better than all our care, the moſt exact words, or all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of Art. The difficulty is to know and diſtinguiſh it; when we have ſufficient force of ſpirit and underſtanding to know it, we need not be much troubled to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the ſcruples which may ariſe from the negligence of certain pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in our Diſcourſe, which regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ought not to have been neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65667:36"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>There are alſo certain manners peculiar to the Barr, which are known but to few Orators, for that they are not diſcovered but by a great penetration of ſpirit, a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inquiry into the ſourſes, and in ſtudying with much meditation the great models of Eloquence which we have amongſt the Ancients. Theſe are the extraordinary efforts of this Art, which ſurprizeth the Judges, and which works unfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen and unexpected effects in their ſpirits: Such was that which <hi>Cicero</hi> praiſes in one <hi>Canus Ruffius,</hi> who being accuſed with much vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence by <hi>Siſenna,</hi> cryed out with a very touching and animated voyce to the Judges, <hi>O ye Judges, I am cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented, except ye ſuccour me, &amp;c.</hi> That ſhew of fear that he had to be ſurprized, and the protection he ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65667:36"/>paſſionately demanded of his Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, touched them ſo much, that they became favourable to him. There are an infinite of like places in <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Cicero;</hi> but we muſt make reflection that theſe are not the gliſtering parts of an Oration, or that ſplendour of words that works theſe effects. Theſe Charms of Eloquence are more in the things themſelves, than in the words; whoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we cannot unfold, nor give cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rules to it, for that they are inexplicable: yet we cannot fail, (if we have a right judgment,) of a true diſcovery. Somtime in theſe great Subjects of Eloquence, we muſt imitate that Maſter-piece of the Painter, who to expreſs the grief of <hi>Agamemnon</hi> at the ſacrifice of his Daughter, drew him with his face covered, deſpairing that his Art could expreſs the ſorrows of a Father, after he had expreſt that of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65667:37"/>his friends in a manner ſo vigorous. Theſe alſo are the expreſſions that <hi>Cicero</hi> requires in matters of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Significatio ſaepe major erit quam oratio.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. in Brut</note> Theſe places ought to be prepared by a paſſionate and tender Diſcourſe, and by all the moſt ſtudied attractions of that Art, to have that ſucceſs that they ought to have.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>Nothing hath ſo much power on the ſpirit of his Judges,<note place="margin">Melior moderatio et nonnun quam etiam patientia bonus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercator vitio ira cundiae carcat. <hi>Quint. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> as the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a general probity, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a moderation in the affairs which wound his own Intereſt, or that of his Party. An affair becomes ſuſpected, when it is mannaged with tranſportation; and Choller may ruine the moſt juſt Cauſe; for we are apt to believe that Cauſe to be unjuſt, which uſeth only paſſion for its defence. Moderation, above
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65667:37"/>all other vertues, knows the beſt how to regulate the outward moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wherewith we are the moſt ſenſibly touched: And indeed they muſt have a very ill opinion of their Judg, who think him capable to take pleaſure in their Choller, and in their ill humour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Loci ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nec erudita ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerabiles, <hi>Cic.</hi>
                  </note>Nothing ſo ill conſiſts with the Eloquence of the Barr, as that fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les cumber of Common Places, wherewith our Pleaders ſwell their Diſcourſe beyond proportion, and ſerves only to weary the patience of the Judg, and make him diſtaſt that which may be good in the reſt. They are ordinarily the young men that are moſt ſubject to this default; they wander about, becauſe they want force of ſpirit to enter imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into the matter: We ſhould render them a great ſervice, if we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65667:38"/>could make them reſolve to leave that length and circuit of Diſcourſe which is ſo much contrary to deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, and becomes odious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable. A Diſcourſe ſpun out with theſe childiſh amplifications, becomes languiſhing, it only makes the Judges yawn, and lulls them into a ſlumber.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>It is alſo the delight of young men to gliſter in all they ſay: But true Eloquence ſeeks not after that vain ſplendour, which is only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to dazle the ſpirit. We alwayes fall into errour when we ſtudy too much to pleaſe. That Lawyer which relies more upon a paſſage of <hi>Seneca</hi> for defence of his Cauſe, than upon good Reaſon, very much deceives himſelf; thoſe gliſtering paſſages have not any force to perſwade, they ſerve only to waken the ſpirit
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65667:38"/>of the Judge, when it is weary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>We ſeldome take any care of the exteriour part which relates to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Cicero</hi> calls the Eloquence of the Body, whoſe perfection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the geſture and pronunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe we do not enough com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the neceſſity and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof: <hi>Quintilian</hi> only hath given us any precepts of it, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, poſſibly believing that it was a gift only of Nature, which could not be reduced into Art or Method, and have contented themſelves only to note us the importance of it, which they have done in ſeveral places of their works. This right pronunciation is ſo important, that we cannot neglect it without renouncing what is moſt powerful and perſwaſive in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65667:39"/>Eloquence: It is that which rules moſt in Diſcourſe, and which irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtibly invades the ſoul, and in which conſiſts the greateſt force and ornament. The great Talent of <hi>Hortenſius</hi> who equall'd <hi>Cicero</hi> in Reputation, was the skilful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the action: He was ſo admirable in an ardent manner of ſpeaking, that <hi>Roſcius</hi> and <hi>Aeſop,</hi> the moſt famous Comedians of that time, went alwayes to hear his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, to learn from him their meaſure. Having ſo little care to form our ſelves to this action, we need not be aſtoniſhed that we ſee ſo few tracts of that Eloquence which wrought ſo many wonders in the Times of <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it henes,</hi> who alwayes endeavour'd to expreſs in themſelves, by their ardour and vehemence, thoſe paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they intended to excite in the Spirits of their Auditors. It is true we have ſeen Orators
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65667:39"/>ſome years paſt, who gave weight to all their Reaſons by the force wherewith they animated their Diſcourſe: but after all, their ardency was ſo ill mannaged, that what they ſaid, loſt its grace, by the deſire they had to be too paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate: for when once the fire mounted to their faces, we could underſtand no more, their pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation became ſo confus'd by their exceſſive tranſport. Some others appear too cold, they ſhew in their greateſt affairs little of that emoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is neceſſary to enflame the ſpirit of the Judges, which are not at all touched in theſe great Subjects, but by great movements. We may ſay to theſe languiſhing Declamators that of <hi>Cicero</hi> againſt <hi>Calidius,</hi> who ſpoke things very touching with an air of tranquility, <hi>An iſta ſi vera eſſent, ſic a te dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentar?</hi> All thoſe which ſpeak at the Barr are ſubject to add to the evil
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65667:40"/>pronunciation, which they learn'd at the Colledg; One conſtant and diſagreeable tone, and an impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the accent in the <hi>penultima</hi> ſyllables, which occaſions rather laughter than perſwaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>The Subjects which furniſh the preſent condition of the <hi>Bar,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of great or elevated, cannot give to Eloquence thoſe advantages, which is found in the more important matters of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients: Such were the deliberations of War and Peace, the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the good of the State and the publick intereſt, the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and defenſes of Princes and Kings, which the great Orators diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with ſo much ſplendour. The intereſts which are at this time the Subjects of the <hi>Barr,</hi> are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo little conſiderable that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65667:40"/>they are not capable to furniſh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch worth to Eloquence, as made it in thoſe times to triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hearts.<note place="margin">His acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat ſpl endot rerum, &amp; magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſa plurimum elo quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia praeſlat. <hi>Dialog. de couſ. co. eloq.</hi> Creſcit cum amplitudine rerum vis ingenij: nee quiſquam illuſtrem orationem facere poteſt, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi qui cauſam paremi invenit. 16.</note> This was one of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages (that <hi>Meſſalla</hi> notes in the Dialogue of <hi>Quintilian</hi>) the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Orators had above thoſe of his time: in effect, petty Subjects make petty Orators; and the Spirit of him that ſpeaks in publick, is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated by the merit and elevation of the Subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>There is an Eloquence of pure Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which is of very great uſe at the <hi>Bar;</hi> and though it be not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſionate, and its manner of declaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be cold, and ſerious, yet it has the dignity that is required to imprint reſpect and veneration; we heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to it as to an Oracle, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingaged
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65667:41"/>in its favour. This is the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence of the Judges, and thoſe which make Orations to Princes and great Lords, who ought to obſerve this calm and peaceful Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, who muſt ſpeak without emotion to preſerve their Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for it ought to have nothing in it but ſubmiſſive and reſpective, and ought to be regulated according to the rank and quality of thoſe to whom it is addreſſed, either more or leſs reſpectively, according to their degree or merit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65667:41"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Eloquence OF THE PULPIT</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is a thing above wonder, that in ſo great a number of Perſons who apply themſelves to Preaching, we find ſo few who ſucceed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have ſo many advantages infinitely above all others who ſpeak in publick. The Eloquence of the Barr cannot furniſh its Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors with matters ſo important to treat, with things ſo touching to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65667:42"/>ſpeak, nor with ſuch great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to perſwade, as this Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the Pulpit: all thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines which ſhe imployes in moving the Paſſions are ſo powerful, the Figures of Rhetorick (which are as ſanctifyed in the Mouth, by the commerce it has with the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) ſo glorious, and the myſteries that it unfolds are ſo tranſcendent, and it ſpeaks by the dignity of its Character with ſo much authority; that if there be any Eloquence which is perfect Miſtreſs of hearts, by the power that it hath to move, and by its natural independance, it muſt be this; from whence comes it then that we have ſo few good Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers? It is not the fault of the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſince Faith prepares their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to a perfect ſubmiſſion to what they come to hear? the ſight of Altars inſpires them with reſpect, and they are already perſwaded by the principles of their Religion,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65667:42"/>of what they come to attend. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſince the Preacher ſpeaks as the Ambaſſadour of God, and his words are the words of his eternal Maſter, when he preaches everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing recompence to thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive, and threatens unſpeakable puniſhments to thoſe who disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive; it muſt be his own fault if he have not all the ſucceſs that his function merits. But as it is too true that amongſt all Profeſſions, there are the feweſt in this who ſucceed well in this Art, it will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to ſearch out the way to remedy it, ſince it is a thing of ſo great importance, which I pretend to do by theſe following Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>We ſeldome enter into ſerious conſideration of that diſpoſition of mind, which the honneſs of that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65667:43"/>miniſtry of the word of God, and the dignity of a Function ſo ſacred, requires. There is not only expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient a great Application, and long ſtudy to repleniſh the mind with great Images, which are neceſſary to form the Character of this Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; but there muſt be alſo long retirements from the noiſe of the World, to prepare the heart by ſolitude for the reception of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, whoſe Interpreter the Preacher takes upon himſelf to be: It is from this eternal Spirit that he takes his immediate miſſion by the principles of the interiour life,<note place="margin">Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabunt niſi mittantur. 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</note> to diſpoſe him to take his <hi>Orders</hi> from thoſe who are eſtabliſhed in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and have received the power of God to communicate it to others: He muſt then take great care that he be not too much abandoned to himſelf and to his Genius; but firſt he muſt paſſionately ſeek the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of Heaven, by the frequent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65667:43"/>uſe of Meditation and Prayer. Without this divine aſſiſtance it is impoſſible to penetrate into the myſteries and hidden truths of the Goſpel. How many does this? who ever thinks of it? what ſtudies or what retreats do we make to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our hearts? or what prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Spirit do we bring to this holy Function? do not we ſee eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day young Preachers without Virtue or Science aſcend the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, with the ſame end that a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maedian</hi> mounts the Theater? they invite their Friends by Letters, and fill a great Circle with their Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who engage a great aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of their honeſt acquaintance, to grace the audience and to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage thoſe young Declamators; they raiſe their Eyes to Heaven with a feigned complaiſance and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit admiration, when they have pronounced two or three ill ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rang'd periods without ſtumbling;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65667:44"/>and when they have a little confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſaid what poſſibly them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have not the courage to act; when theſe trifling Orators have done what they can, they are but pittied by thoſe who judge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preoccupation, even in thoſe performances wherein they think they have reaſon to triumph. They have a very falſe <hi>Idea</hi> of ſo holy a Function; if they think to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance its reverence by ſuch preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, a Preacher muſt have other qualities to enable him to repreſent with ſucceſs the Sword of Gods word like a flame to the Eyes of the Offendors, to reduce, <hi>Libertines</hi> under the ſacred Yoke of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and to caſt into our Spirits the terrour of the laſt Judgement, by a vigorous repreſentation of the pains of Hell, and the dreadful conſequence of our unbeleif, and to ſuſtain in ſome ſort the Dignity, Grandeur and Majeſty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65667:44"/>whereof our Religion makes profeſſion. It is alſo without doubt for this reaſon, that the two Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Lord were called the Children of Thunder: for the word of God which they proclaimed, with that dignity which it merited, was bright and terrible in their Mouths. Few of our Declamators are thus qualified, they uſually Preach for their recreation, or to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Injunctions of their Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, to diſcharge themſelves of ſome troubleſome Fat: theſe are profanations ſo deplorable that we ſhould with great difficulty beleive it, had we not ſo many examples of it in this Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>We do not enough conſider that it is on Gods account we ſpeak when we Preach, by which means we deprive the Word of its weight
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65667:45"/>and authority; for the greateſt part of Preachers ſpeak only of their Patrons; to whom they make a merchandiſe of themſelves, and extinguiſh in ſome manner the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, to give place entirely to their own exorbitant and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, Fancies. This was not the practice of the antient Prophets, who were the Preachers of the old Law, they ſpoke not as private men to the People,<note place="margin">Pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto legati one fungi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam deo exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante per nos, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> but as men ſent from God; and the grandeur of that Maſter whoſe commands they delivered, attracted the reſpect of their Auditors. I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſeen an Ambaſſador of a petty ſtranger Prince, who had no Talent in ſpeaking, but becauſe he was to ſpeak on the account of his Maſter, he aſſumed on himſelf an air of authority by which he procured at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and perſwaded meerly by the addreſs he had to make himſelf conſidered: What weight then
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65667:45"/>ſhould we give to the Word of God, if we know the Art to treat of it as the word of God, and not as a pure invention of the wit of man? he therefore that would Preach the Word with ſucceſs, muſt do as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Per arma Juſtitiae in verbo veritatis in virtute Dei,</hi> Cor. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>As this ſacred Eloquence travels in a Feild infinitely more large than Eloquence profane; It propoſes an eternal Kingdome for the object of our hopes; and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which indure for ever, of our fears and caution. The ſanctity of our myſteries, the purity of our morality, the Majeſty of the God which we adore, of whom we find ſo many great <hi>Idaea's</hi> in the holy Scripture, and all thoſe glorious Truths which render our Religion ſo auguſt, are the moſt ordinary Subjects wherein this divine Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65667:46"/>is exerciſed. It demands alſo, to work the effects which it propoſes to it ſelf, greater natural qualities, and a genius more eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted than is required in humane Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. A Preacher therefore ought to have great exteriour qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Gravity in all his Perſon, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in his countenance, Devotion in his Eyes, a certain ardeur in his Pronunciation, a Freedome in all his Action, and the Air of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; but a ſole aſſembly of theſe exteriour qualities, is ſo rare, that I have not known a Preacher in this Age that came near this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except one; this one had an excellent natural diſpoſition for Preaching joyned with the vivaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of imagination, and a fineneſs of Spirit, which he poſſeſſed in a ſoveraign degree, and which gave him a wonderful facility in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf, the greateſt that I have ever ſeen in any perſon; he
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65667:46"/>had yet a Talent in pronunciation the moſt extraordinary in the world, that one might ſay that he was an Orator in his countenance, in his voice, in his geſture, and in all his actions; he could make his Eyes with an eaſie motion ſpeak any thing, give an inflection to his voice, an air to his viſage, any grace to his geſture, and an agreement to to his diſcourſe, ſuch as he pleaſed; and all theſe in ſuch a degree as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had Orator an equal power to him to raiſe attention, and as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any perſon was more Maſter of what he ſaid, nor of the manner wherein he ſpoke; he could give to the Spirits of his audience what impreſſions he pleaſed. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places where he Preached was too little to hold the concourſe of thoſe that followed him. Though this great facility he had in ſpeaking betrayed him into a neglect of preparing himſelf, yet by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65667:47"/>the mere power of his action in the moſt indifferent and neglected diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, he could impoſe upon the People by his manner of ſpeaking: the moſt common things that he ſaid, were liſtend to with the ſame applauſe and admiration, as thoſe which were the moſt extraordinary things the choiſeſt Preachers could ſay. He had certainly been the moſt accompliſhed Preacher that ever was, had his judgment and his capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city anſwered to his other Talents; and if he had not been ſo exceſſive in his action, which was too ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and beſides had not all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity that the ſanctity of the place required.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>Theſe natural Talents ſometimes exert themſelves in ſo much ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that they rob (if it be lawful ſo to ſpeak) the word of God of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65667:47"/>that eſteem &amp; veneration which we ought to have for it; they often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelves attention, not for that it is on Gods account they ſpeak,<note place="margin">Non in ſapientia verbi, ne. vacuetur crux Chriſti. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> but becauſe they ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably, becauſe they are Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, Preach novelties, or bear ſome Character of dignity or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in the Church, or for ſome other out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard qualities, like the People of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who went to hear <hi>Ezekiel</hi> becauſe he was Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. For this reaſon it was that Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> went firſt to hear Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> before he was converted. The Preacher ought to ſhun, as a thing too humane, and too ſenſual, the giving place in his diſcourſe to the curioſity of the people; which he may eaſily do, in taking the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to profit, rather than pleaſe. He cannot faile too of ſucceſs, if he know how to ſpeak of good things, and to ſpeak them with judgement and knowledge.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:65667:48"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§ 5.</head>
               <p>I do not intend that it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for all thoſe that are called to the miniſtry to have all thoſe great qualities that I have numbred; 'tis good that in the Church there ſhould be men of different capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to be accommodated to thoſe of their Auditors, which are ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: It ſuffices to a Preacher that preaches to the common People, to know the principal duties of Chriſtianity. An indifferent Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is ſufficiently qualified to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Religion, and make it ſubſiſt in a Village, maugre the ignorance and ſtupidity that reigns amongſt us; for that mediocrity of genius, may always be in an eſtate to inſtruct, eſpecially if it have joyned with it any Talent inſpeaking; and though he want the Genius to raiſe deep concernments, yet he may be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65667:48"/>numbred amongſt thoſe Preachers who have the power to make a great noiſe by an animated manner of ſpeaking, which oftentimes works the ſame effect upon the hearts of the People, as the Drums and Trumpets do upon the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in a Battel: The noiſe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes them, and makes them run with precipitation upon the Enemy, without any reflection whither they go. It is not the impulſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> which moves the groſſer Spirits and awakens them to their duty, for they underſtand it not; but it is the emotion and ardeur with which they ſpeak, and the loudneſs of their Exclamations, which makes the impreſſion; it is not the things themſelves that move, but the manner of delivering them, becauſe the manner is ſenſible, and the things are not: It is alſo manifeſt that the People judge not ſo much by the reaſons (as hath been ſaid)
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65667:49"/>as by the tone of the voice; they beleive him that ſpeaks moſt loud, and with moſt confidence; and it is to this boldneſs that they owe the ſucceſs of their perſwaſions: for the truth is, the Soul is not ordinarily moved, than by what firſt vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſtrikes the ſenſe. But after all this, theſe popular Preachers muſt be let to underſtand, that they become ridiculous when they ſtrive to be numbred amongſt the fine Spirits, and endeavour rather to pleaſe, than to edifie; it ſuffices in Preaching to the People, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſimply to them the great veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion, and the ſanctity of its morals, without labouring ſo much for Forms and Ornaments, which oftentimes ſerve only to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the Preacher as well as his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65667:49"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§ 6.</head>
               <p>The moſt part of Preachers are rendred very ignorant, by mingling themſelvs too much in the commerce of the world, neglecting to apply themſelves (with that diligence that is required) to the work of the Miniſtry; 'tis this reduces them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oa neceſſity, to copy one from another, to furniſh themſelves with matters for their Sermons. They take not the pains to fetch it from the Sources, nor indeed have they any knowledge of them; this is the cauſe that they uſe ſuch ill Reaſons to perſwade to vertue, for they have not a capacity for good reaſons, nor the Art to make them underſtood when they have them. They uſually ruine themſelves by this copying from other men, and extinguiſh their own Genius, by ſtriving to aſſume that of others: From hence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65667:50"/>I may ſay, all thoſe deformities which are ſo ordinary amongſt them, firſt receive their birth; &amp; that which makes ſo many ill Preachers, is the falſe method they chooſe; they ought not to ſerve themſelves with the deſigns, nor the thoughts of others, till they be able to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them and make them proper to their own Spirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>This Eloquence only becomes ſolid in a great capacity, nor can any hope to be fortunate in this Art, who has not before repleniſhed his mind, with all the knowledges neceſſary to treat the word of God with dignity: The moſt important is that of Divinity, without which a Preacher cannot with that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and authority give clear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions in the ſubjects whereof he treats. It is a great weakneſs in him
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65667:50"/>that preaches, when he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine preciſely what is of Faith, and what is not, or to heſitate, when he ſhould decide. But we know that there is nothing more great, neceſſary or agreeable in this Eloquence of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> than Divinity, which is the Science of Religion, and there is nothing more miſerable and diſguſting, when it is not treated with that ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and dignity with which it ought to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>A too frequent commerce with the Schoolmen, brings a much greater prejudice than advantage to the Preacher, when he knows not how to make uſe of it as he ought, and wants Wiſdome or a neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution in the reading of them; for there is nothing ſo contrary to Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as the learning of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65667:51"/>Schools, and I am perſwaded that the Lecture of <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> how ſolid and methodick ſoever he be, hath made more ill Preachers than good, for he writ in a very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable age, whoſe guſt was univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted; and that difficult man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that he hath to expreſs things, is as much oppoſed to Eloquence, as the things themſelves are proper; for though a ſimple and plain ſtile is fitteſt for inſtruction, yet it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes very much contrary to what we ought to uſe in publick, if we take not great care. The Divines which ſucceeded him, have imitated the ſame manner, and it is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the general method of the Schools, and ſo dangerous to this kind of Eloquence; it is buſied only in deſertations and ſubtilties, which may perhaps give the Nerves and force to diſcourſe, but deprives it of the grace and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; hence it appears that Logick
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65667:51"/>though it teach the Art of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet it is not abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Eloquence; for though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it a diſcourſe is but a pratling in the Air, which ſignifies nothing: yet its ſuccours are not to be received in that naked manner which is uſual; they muſt be clad in the Ornaments of Eloquence, to add a grace to its diſcourſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>There may be made the ſame ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon the writings of the Latin Fathers, which are alſo much contrary to Eloquence, by reaſon of the miſerable eſtate of thoſe times, in which they writ; every one knows to what extremities, all that which was call'd good ſenſe, was reduc'd to at the time of the departure of the <hi>Barbarians</hi> from <hi>Italy:</hi> All the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the firſt age, even to Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> have writ after this hard
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65667:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>and dry manner, excepting a very little number which are not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by this <hi>Guſto,</hi> by reaſon of ſome tincture which they have conſerved, as <hi>Minutius Felix, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian, Arnobius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> &amp; St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> to which we might add ſome places in the works of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi> The Greek Fathers are more Eloquent than the Latine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though the order of their deſigns, and the matters which they treat on are very little juſt or conformable to the precepts of Art; for they have taken an Air of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, more natural and eaſie, but thereby they become more apt to be abandoned to their Genius, as we may obſerve in Saint <hi>Baſile,</hi> and in Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome;</hi> Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzen</hi> is indeed more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and without doubt has more of Art; but when I advertiſe the Preachers of the danger of reading of the Latine Fathers (by expoſing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65667:52"/>their Eloquence) to the end to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to take caution that they ruine not themſelves on that part, I pretend not to decry all commerce with them, which is not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but abſolutely neceſſary for a Preacher to furniſh his Spirit with Idea's of ſanctity, and of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of our Religion, which we find in all the works of theſe Authors. In the reading of theſe, the moſt pure of the Chriſtian morality is to be found; from whence the Preacher may draw it, as from the proper ſource, the moſt clear and undiſturbed, The Fathers are the Interpreters of the Evangeliſts, and the Church honours them with the Title of holy, becauſe their works are as a heritage and patrimony which they have bequeathed to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as to their true Children.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:65667:53"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>'Tis not enough that the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher lay a foundation by a long ſtudy of Divinity, and a frequent reading of the Fathers, which he ought to do with method; but he muſt alſo ſtudy a Rhetorick proper to the Pulpit, whereof we find not any Character amongſt the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, who have not had any perfect Idea of it; nor amongſt the Moderns, who have only copyed from the Antients. The Majeſty of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Sanctity of its Laws, the purity of its Morality, its exalted Myſteries, and the importance of all its Subjects, ought to give it an elevation which cannot be ſuſtain'd by the weakneſs of a ſpirit purely humane. It is in vain to ſearch for it in the Rhetorick of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in the Idea's of <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> or in the Inſtitutions of <hi>Quintilian,</hi> even
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65667:53"/>that ſublime kind which <hi>Longinus</hi> hath formed of all the great expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Antients which he hath collected, are feeble, and low in compariſon of that which our Preacher ought to poſſeſs to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the dignity of his Character. That divine Air which the grandeur of Chriſtian Religion, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibility of our Faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, is only to be ſought in thoſe excellent Idea's which are to be found in the holy Scripture by thoſe who know the ſecret to penetrate into the depth thereof. This is that pure and plentiful Spring from whence all thoſe magnificent expreſſions flow, whoſe Author is the holy Spirit. It is from hence he ought to take thoſe glorious Images, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levation which makes up the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Character of this Eloquence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he muſt read with diligence the Prophets, and lay out his time in hourly meditations of them, if he
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65667:54"/>would preach terror,<note place="margin">Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plus valet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum timor quam ſpes bonorum <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8</note> which muſt be his moſt general practice; for to preach well, he muſt terrifie the Sinner, and awaken him from the Lethargy &amp; ſoftneſs of a vitious age, by caſting a terror into his Spirit. To this I add, that the Scripture is a Fountain abounding with all the Riches, and all the Ornaments, whereof this Eloquence is formed; and that all kinds of writing are there to be found: <hi>Eſaiah</hi> is elevated, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> moving, <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> terrible, <hi>Daniel</hi> tender, and all the other Prophets in general contain ſomething ſo great and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, as is not in any meaſure to be equall'd by what is moſt eſteemed in prophane Orators. Good ſenſe and right reaſon, was never ſo clearly unvayl'd in any work of morality, as in the Books of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> never hath any Hiſtory been writ with an Air more ſimple and elevated, mixed together, nor in a manner more perfect than that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65667:54"/>of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereof <hi>Longinus</hi> only cites two words in the beginning of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 8</note> to give the greateſt and moſt ſublime Idea that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is capable of, ſo far above the higheſt elevation of profane Authors. Never was any thing writ more tender or delicate, for the thoughts of Devotion &amp; Piety, than the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David:</hi> the moſt refined politicks and worldly wiſdom, are to be found in the Book of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Proverbs:</hi> Finally, nothing has been ever conceived in the utmoſt extent of humane capacity, more profound and penetrating than thoſe ſacred and adorable myſteries of Grace, and predeſtination, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath delivered in his Epiſtles. And to ſay a word of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which is the moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Book of our Religion, to which all that hath been writ by the Prophets is but Preface and Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; what can one ſay more great or expreſſive than what our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65667:55"/>Saviour himſelf ſaid in two words, <hi>Verba quae locutus ſum vobis Spiritus &amp; vita ſunt?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 6.</note> all the other Books may be ſaid to contain only words, but this is a rich Treaſury of things: And as it is the Character of the Spirit of man, to ſpeak much, and in effect to ſay little; ſo 'tis the Character of the holy Spirit to ſpeak little, and therein to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend much: all the holy Scripture hath in it moſt excellent things couch'd in the moſt humble and ſimple expreſſions, which ordinarily enlarge our conceptions beyond the Letter. What is more plain and more ſuccinct then theſe words, <hi>Verbum caro factum eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.</note> —<hi>&amp; cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixerunt eum?</hi> how many Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hath been made upon theſe words, how many diſſertations at this day? how great muſt then be the penetration of Spirit, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to diſcover the depth of Theſe Myſteries? We ſtay our ſelves
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65667:55"/>upon the ſuperficies of words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſearching to the bottom, by meditation. Who is at this day a Preacher ſo illuminated, to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into all theſe myſterious dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and holy obſcurities of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, to diſcover the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Treaſures thereof? alaſs our want comes from our little meditation thereof.<note place="margin">Parvuli petierunt panem, &amp; non erat qui fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret cis. <hi>Lament. Jer. c.</hi> 4.</note> It is the unhappineſs of this age, that there are ſo few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons found capable to break the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bread of Gods word, which ought to be the moſt ordinary nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the faithful; that is to ſay, there are few Preachers ſo illuminated, as to unfold the whole ſenſe of the holy Scripture to the People; or who know how to make uſe of Art, which is the moſt certain means to ſucceed in their Preaching; they Preach their own Imagination and thoughts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning the thoughts of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit. Is not this to be wanting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65667:56"/>in the principals? for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a true Idea of Chriſtian Eloquence, but from the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is the firſt original.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>There is required (beſides this reading of the Fathers, &amp; a diligent ſtudy of Divinity, joyned with that Art of Eloquence, which is formed upon that of the Prophets, that the Preacher forms a morality, whereof the principles muſt be taken from the Goſpel; for all other morality is no more than a certain Pagan pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, and pure Philoſophy. This is not only to be found by the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Evangeliſts, but as well in the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and in the Homilies of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> where it is ſo well explained: Theſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies ought to be the moſt ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtudy of the Preacher, whereof alſo he will find great inſtructions in Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> Saint
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65667:56"/>
                  <hi>Gregory,</hi> the great, in Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi> This diligence ought not to be in the ſearch after beautiful thoughts, and ſhining words, which is the fault of moſt young Preachers, which in truth conduce little to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People, or true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>This true morality cannot be taken then from theſe pure and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſources, whereof I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, eſpecially in theſe times, where every one frames to himſelf morals according to his own fantaſie; and we find ſo many extravagant Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, who impoſe from the Pulpit their own moroſe humours and ſour temperaments for pure morality, which are accompanied with the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Viſions, which their Spirit of novelty, or their preoccupation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires. Have we not ſeen ſome Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65667:57"/>who notwithſtanding their profound ignorance in all that a Preacher ought to know, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a deciſion of all things, with the utmoſt rigour, and deliver, with the aſſurance of a Prophet and an unparalel'd confidence, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt abſurdities in the World, and in matters of morality to hazzard every novelty, when the Smoak of their Zeal has once mounted to their heads</p>
               <p>'Tis the cuſtome of our Nation to run after all that is new, or that has any air of ſingularity; but when we have ſounded the depth of thoſe Preachers, who practice (to derive reſpect on their diſcourſes) an affectation of ſeverity on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, we ſhall find that they are not altogether ſo hard to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as they are to others. Such a one was a young Doctor, who Preached five years ago before an honourable Audience; who who commenc'd his Sermon by
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:65667:57"/>promiſing in a tone of a Reformator that he would Preach nothing but ſevere morality, and the pure ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Goſpel; and a little after he canted forth the ſtory of the new Pope, wherein he forgot nothing that might rejoyce or give a ſubject for entertainment to the more ſportive part of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Thoſe that would Preach this ſeverity muſt do as Jeſus Chriſt has done, that is to ſay, Preach by his example. The Character of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſeverity is to be ſweet to others and hard to our ſelves; to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is to play the Impoſtor or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moedian, not a Preacher. We have ſeen in this paſt age, falſe Zealots who made profeſſion to preach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n morality more rigid than others; during which they were lifting up their impure hands to Heaven, and fomenting errour upon Earth. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe Preachers who are ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, only becauſe they are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and who make Enormities
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65667:58"/>and abominations of mere trifles, who will damn a Woman for wearing of Lace or colour'd Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, or for having been a prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nading upon a Feſtival day; theſe Preachers I ſay diſhonour their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, by the exceſs of their ſottiſh exaggerations; they diſcourage the faithful by making falſe Images of crime, and authorize Libertiniſm by theſe terrible <hi>Ideas</hi> they give of Vertue; whereby they render it more dreadful and ſalvage than it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>The little ſucceſs that moſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers meet with, comes from the little care they have to underſtand the morals of our Religion; and the ſmall Talent they have in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing it for nothing, ſo ſenſibly touches the Spirits, as the pourtracts which we make, when we make them well, in which we are oft rendred
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65667:58"/>wanting by a vain curioſity, and a too ſcrupulous kind of ratiocinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This way we take to ſhun the difficulty we find in the well painting of manners, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h is a thing not only the moſt capable to attract admiration to the Orator, but alſo the moſt difficult to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this, he muſt commence by a perfect knowledge of the heart of man, he muſt know the particular of all its motions; to make a true pourtraict, and to paint men ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally that they may know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Pictures that are made of them. 'Tis in this that almoſt all Preachers are wanting, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent falſe Images of manners to their Auditors, in making them too difficult, or too eaſie, ſo that they faile of the intended ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for that the Images being falſe we know them not; and what he ſayes is quite loſt, becauſe no perſon can take it as ſpoken to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65667:59"/>himſelf; they Preach to the rich as to the poor, to the Courtier as to the Citizen, they make the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of a City the Subject of a Village Sermon; and they make elaborate Sermons, where ſimple Catechiſmes and naked inſtructions are moſt proper. Every one knows the ſtory, of the Preacher, who preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the ſpecies of ſin againſt the ſixth Commandment, to a houſe of Religion. This is the moſt ordinary defect of the whole Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, becauſe the neceſſary diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and underſtanding of the perſons to whom they ſpeak, and the perfect knowledge of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of men are Talents very rare; for the great experience of the world which he muſt have, joyned with the light of Phyloſophy and Divinity, (which are the firſt ſour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this diſcernment) are the moſt eſſential to a Preacher, and I am
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65667:59"/>perſwaded that none can ſucceed, but according to the proportion of his knowledge of the manners and heart of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 14.</head>
               <p>The heart of man is an abyſm of unknown Depth; whatſoever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries we make, ſtill there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſomthing not yet diſcovered. It is not alone ſufficient to make a true picture, though we had ſo much power of penetration, as to know its impoſtures, deceits, diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, weakneſſes, ſuſpitions, its diſtaſts, jealouſies, irreſolutions, its ſeveral Meanders, and inequalities, its delicateſſes which ſurmount inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, its pride, preſumption, and that confus'd Miſcellany of all its affections, and finally, its natural and inconceivable propenſion to malice and diſguiſement. He muſt yet know how to take off the mask
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65667:60"/>of vertue, of candor, and ſincerity, which are uſed in the more ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and refined exerciſes of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; he muſt make him ſee that by his ſelf love (againſt which all the Fathers have declaimed with ſo much heat) and by a falſe mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty which he conceales from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the evil of his own intentions, to ſhun under this diſguiſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion that it would bring him. And as man hath not any vertue of himſelf, but on the contrary, his nature is corrupted with vice, he muſt ſhew him that the joy which he ſeems to have in the exerciſe of vertue, is but a counterfeit joy; that he flatters himſelf with a falſe appearance of ſorrow and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the exerciſe of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; that his Faith, his Hope, his Charity, and his other vertues, are no other than imaginary, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he amuſes himſelf, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful tranquility amidſt the vain
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65667:60"/>and confuſed projects that he frames of his ſalvation. Finally, for to diſcover him wholly, and to give him a full proſpect of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, he muſt depaint to him his falſe modeſties in the things he ſeeks after, his artificial excuſes in what he flies, the perverſity of his Judgment in what he eſteems, the frailty of his reſolutions, and the continual agitation and inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes in the purſuance of any good: I ſhould never find an end, if I would diſcover all the changes and varieties of his thoughts. I have ſaid enough to make out in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral the principal ſourſe of all its motions, which ought to be the ſubject of a perpetual meditation to him who pretends to be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from other Preachers: For in effect, the knowledg of this heart of man, more or leſs great, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the ſole thing which makes the true diſtinction of the different
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:65667:61"/>Talents of Preaching, in the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of divers manners that there are of preaching. The little care that moſt Preachers take to gain a perfect knowledg of man, is one of the moſt ordinary cauſes that there are ſo few in number of thoſe that ſucceed; for that when they ſpeak things ſo much in the general, and deſcend not in the particular enumeration of Manners, none ſeem to be inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in what they ſay. It is this particularizing of morals, when it is natural, which gives ſucceſs to the Preacher; and as this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret is rare, ſo is the ſucceſs alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 15.</head>
               <p>Beſides this Morallity which is a part of Eloquence, which contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes the moſt to render it admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the Art to excite the Paſſions contributes alſo not a little: For it
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:65667:61"/>ſufficeth not to a Preacher to ſpeak good things, but he muſt ſpeak them well, and with a moving air; for when he ſayes any thing thats touching, without ſeeming moved himſelf, 'tis only taken for a Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mace, wherewith he mocks his Audience. I once heard a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, who preached with words very well choſen, and all that he ſaid was very good; but he ſpoke it ſo coldly, without that action and heat that is neceſſary to work con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, that he gave cauſe to the pleaſant to ſay, that he could not be ſo calm, without being in ſome faſhion reſigned to the Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Auditors, ſince he appear'd to take ſo little intereſt in what he ſaid. And in truth, this cold and languiſhing manner of ſpeaking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the great ſubjects of the Goſpel, is a great obſtacle to the vertue of the Word of God, the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not delivered at leaſt with ſome
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65667:62"/>ſort of zeal and ardeur, failes of his expected fruit. But alaſs, how few Preachers are there, who at this day can boaſt that they have mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the leaſt of their Auditors, by repreſenting the horrour of ſin, and the greatneſs of the pains to which he is deſtined? Though we have known a <hi>Jerome Savan.</hi> in <hi>Flor.</hi> one <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Grenada</hi> in <hi>Sevil,</hi> and one <hi>Delingendes</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> (not to exclude ſom famous men of our own nation) who have made all their Auditors tremble whenſoever they opened their mouthes of matters ſo terrible. Whence proceeds this, but from that languiſhing way of Preaching, whereof the manner is ſo little touching. It is remembred of a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucin</hi> named <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Narny,</hi> who under the Pontificate of <hi>Gregory</hi> 15. preached at <hi>Rome</hi> with ſo much power, ſo much of action, and ſo much of zeal, that he never ſpoke in publick, that he made not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65667:62"/>to be cryed to the people through the ſtreets when they went from the Sermon. It is likewiſe ſaid, that having one day preach't before the Pope of the obligation that Biſhops have to reſide, he ſo terrified by the vehemence of his diſcourſe, thirty Biſhops who were at the Sermon, that the very next day they poſted to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Dioceſſes. Theſe great effects are wrought by an extraordinary talent in pronunciation, to which eloquence oftentimes owes all the doing of its miracles, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common people, whoſe apprehenſions are too groſs to be moved by Eloquence, but only as it is ſenſible: Such is this ardent and pathetick kind of declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this is a thing very little ſtudied becauſe it demands ſo much dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and application, whereof very few perſons are capable, and for which reaſon the greateſt part of Preachers ſcarce ever think on't.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:65667:63"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 16.</head>
               <p>It is but too true, that few Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers allow themſelves time to the exerciſe of pronunciation to form it true, and to grace it with ſutable action; they think altogether on other things; they ſtudy the Fathers, they ſtudy Rhetorick, they ſtudy the Tongues, but they neglect the ſtudy of this Art of action, which only hath the power to animate what he ſays, and to give an agreement neceſſary to ingage the attention of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor. The negligence of this part is alone capable to render all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unprofitable; but yet after all this, there are in this, as in other things, ſome extremities to be fear'd and avoided: For thoſe Preachers who are all paſſionate, and who begin their Exordiums in thunder, leaſt they ſhould ſeem to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any thing, ruine all by giving themſelves too much to their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65667:63"/>humour. It is good to make them comprehend that they never were leſs capable to move, than when they moſt ſtriv'd to do ſo. I have ſometimes ſeen a Preacher who was of this humour, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding preach't with very good ſucceſs: indeed he had a rare talent, and many tracts in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe which did exceedingly affect the ſpirits: His way of ſpeaking was very ſtrong, and his whole aire was vehement, but he loſt theſe great advantages by a too great paſſion that he had to move, and to make vehement diſcourſes againſt the Times, ſo that his declamation became too full of Tranſport, his geſtures too expreſſive, and his countenance too Comaedian; final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his manner was ſo very much corrupted by the Grimaces, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent agitations and conſtraints of his whole body, that all his motions became ſo many real Convulſions. A
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65667:64"/>Preacher muſt ſhun theſe extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant tranſports of zeal, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come blameable as oft as they are exceſſive; he muſt therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well this rule, that he never moves leſs, than when he betrays this too earneſt deſire to his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: it ſeems but a falſe paſſion which indures ſo long; and that zeal becomes ſuſpected which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with ſo much heat, and whereof the Preacher makes too great oſtentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 17.</head>
               <p>There is in moſt a too great deſire to pleaſe without putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the trouble of working real concernments in their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; this is another extremity which ought to be avoided: For he that would perfectly ſucceed in preaching muſt commence by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt the heart before he think
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:65667:64"/>to pleaſe: What way he ſhould take to effect this, I have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. I deny not but that there may be found in this Age a ſpecies of good ſenſe joyned with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things, but by a too great paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that moſt have to pleaſe, they bring themſelves in danger to looſe the true fruit of things, by a too careful ſearch after the flower: For that which pleaſes opens the heart and diſſipates the ſpirits, which only profits by its cloſe entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he looſes what is ſolid by a too eager purſuit of what is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. It is without doubt from that diſpoſition of ſpirit that there are ſo many Preachers who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour more to pleaſe than to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, and who introduce into the Pulpit all thoſe various guſto's which reign in the world, which they make their ſtudy, that they may appear the more <hi>al a mode.</hi> We have lately ſeen many Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65667:65"/>of this kind, who prepare themſelves to go to a Sermon, as to a Ball; where he meets all the fair world aſſembled, whom he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertains with the morality in faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, delivered in an amorous ſtile, and with an aire very laſcivious: What is the effect of theſe agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sermons but the diſſipation of the ſpirits, than which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more oppoſed to devotion. Unhappineſs be to theſe Preachers <hi>al a mode:</hi> The Evangeliſts nor the Apoſtles did not thus: What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decence is it to preach the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Religion, the abjection of Chriſtianity, and the contempt of the Croſs with an aire undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and with fine and ſtudied ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and to mix theſe feeble ornaments with the greatneſs and majeſty of our Religion? This is the moſt ordinary defect of thoſe who preach to perſons of Quality; they amuſe themſelves to make
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65667:65"/>Religion agreeable to the manners of thoſe, whom they ought to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie, in letting them underſtand that their condition hath an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial oppoſition to Salvation, and that they find not any tract or foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep of the Goſpel, or of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in the life that they lead at Court. It is true, he ought to have compaſſion on their blindneſs, who are poyſon'd with a peſtilential aire which reigns amongſt them. But this ought ſo much the more to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Preacher to ſpeak the Truth: For we are taught by the Fathers, that the Court alwayes followed the manners of their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; if they were holy, it fail'd not to be holy alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>There are ſome others who fail of ſucceſs, becauſe their reſpects are too humane and too intereſs'd;
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65667:66"/>they are more attentive to their own eſtabliſhment, than to the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Auditors; they preach themſelves, and not Jeſus Chriſt. Let thoſe Preachers reflect, that the great ſucceſs the of Apoſtles came (as St. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith) from their diſintereſsment. St. <hi>Paul</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected an entire converſion upon the people, becauſe he pretended no benefit by his Sermons: But it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens ſometimes to thoſe who have reſigned all their temporal hopes in renouncing the world, yet have no power to ſubdue this fooliſh va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which makes the Preacher la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor too much after reputation; who after he has renounced all, cannot, without much pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, renounce the pleaſure of being prais'd. Let the Preacher that would cure himſelf of this weakneſs, conſider (if all theſe praiſes that are given him were ſincere, which they ſcarce ever are,) that he has but preach't very
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65667:66"/>indifferently, whilſt he has left ſtill a liberty to his Auditors to ſay that he has done well, and that his preaching is not to much purpoſe; whilſt he hath given them leave to ſay that he hath preached agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, he has only given them a little pleaſure, but no fruit. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt praiſes of a Preacher is the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his Auditors, and when they riſe all penſive from their ſeats after Sermon, and depart from the Church without ſpeaking a word, this is a ſure mark that they are nearly touched. and that they think on what they heard. This agrees with what the Great <hi>Symachus</hi> in one of his Epiſtles ſaid to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours <hi>Theodoſins</hi> and <hi>Arcadius:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſtupo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris locum plauſibus non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquit. <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 22.</note> (The greatneſs of our admiration and aſtoniſhment ſeals up our tongues, and deprives us of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to praiſe) An example of this I have ſeen at the Sermon of a Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who preach't in a manner ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65667:67"/>and touching, that when they departed from the Sermon, and aſtoniſhment of the Auditors, and the compunction of heart which they ſuffered, impoſed a general ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which ſpoke loud to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. I cannot forbear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of an Adventure which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me a few years ago. I went to hear a Sermon one day in Lent to the Court; the Preacher that day preach't upon the paſſion of our Lord with an aire very brisk and poliſh't: The Ladies from time to time lift up their eyes to heaven during his diſcourſe, ſaying, <hi>that was excellently expreſs'd! that was graciouſly ſpoken!</hi> whilſt I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt mad with indignation to hear him diſcourſe ſo pleaſantly in a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſo worthy compaſſion, and take ſo much pains to pleaſe his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, whom he ought to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to affect with grief and compunction. There is one other
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65667:67"/>vanity yet more fooliſh and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. When thoſe that have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a reputation of good men, and to be excellent in this Art, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to themſelves the glory and ſucceſs of their perſwaſions, when they have done no more than what is effected by the impreſſion of the voice, and the exterior part of ſpeech upon the heart: Our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion teaches us, that it is the holy Spirit alone which does the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 19.</head>
               <p>Another cauſe of the ill ſucceſs in preaching, is the Preachers being too much abandon'd to himſelf, without ever thinking to implore the aſſiſtance and ſuccours of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; whereby he is driven to mix his own imaginations and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes with the grandeur and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Myſteries: like that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Preacher, who preach't
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65667:68"/>one day very miſerably before a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhop, making this comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after Sermon, <hi>that he was forced to abandon himſelf to the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe he had been allowed but a little time for preparation: Adding that hereafter he hoped to acquit himſelf better.</hi> There is ſomething ſo great and elevated, which I know not how to name, in our Myſteries, that it ſuffices to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them ſimply, and without Art, to the people, to merit all the glory that can be hoped from Eloquence, (were it honeſt to preach for Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 20.</head>
               <p>He treats unworthily the Word of God, who debaſes himſelf to the childiſh amplifications of petty ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and to meer trifles, amongſt the great number of important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which furniſh our Religion;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65667:68"/>following the example of thoſe trifling Preachers, who ſpend their Zeal againſt Paintings, Garnitures, Dreſſes, and other vanities of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. A good man begins by throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a terror into our Souls, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Judgments of God, and making us tremble by proclaiming the dreadful conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of our Sins; this is the moſt powerful means to extirpate Luxury, and the moſt capable to introduce Modeſty in our Habits and Behaviour: He does but trifle, that thinks to effect it any other way. And in truth, in ſo great and rich abundance of great matters which the Goſpel affords, he muſt have a very low ſpirit who can ſtay and buſie himſelf about ſuch trivial ſubjects. I know not by what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs our Preachers become ſo nugatory in the great ſubjects they have to treat; when the antient Pagans were even great and eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65667:69"/>in the leaſt things that they had to ſay.</p>
               <p>I am aſhamed when I read the Oration of <hi>Eſchines</hi> againſt <hi>Cteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> where that Orator makes ſhine with ſo much Art the power of a Pagan Eloquence in theſe Trifles. <hi>We</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are come to the Feaſt of</hi> Corbeils; <hi>the Victims are upon the Altars, the Sacrifice is ready, and you are all prepared to beg of the Gods what is neceſſary for the State: But conſider before with what voice, with what ſpirit, and with what aſſurance you can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your Vows, if you leave the Impiety of thoſe who have viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Myſteries, unpuniſh'd.</hi> See how much ſpirit, and how much greatneſs there is in ſolittle a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, in compariſon of that languor and weakneſs of moſt part of our Preachers; who inſtead of being elevated by the Majeſty and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Myſteries, amuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65667:69"/>in little things, becauſe they have not that force of ſpirit to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten upon the greater; The grave and ſerious kind is the character moſt eſſential to the Pulpit, which admits of nothing that is low, cold, trivial, or childiſh; to obtain this he muſt imitate the Apoſtle, who in lieu of buſying himſelf in the ſearch of prophane Ornaments, made all his Art and all his Eloquence out of the continual meditation of the greatneſs of Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Non do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas fabulas ſeculi, notam fecimus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Jeſu Chriſti virtutem, ſpeculatores facti illius magnitudinis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 21.</head>
               <p>The moſt refined and ſublime matters are not the moſt proper for preaching; but on the contrary, thoſe that are the moſt edifying and ſimple: For theſe reaſons we ought to blame that extravagancy of wit
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:65667:70"/>which reigns in this age, and labours after curious deſigns, and ingenious diſtributions and diviſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which gains ſo much appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation from the Ladies. Such was that diviſion of the Preacher, who preaching on the ſuffering of our Saviour, thought he had acquitted himſelf very dexterouſly, when he had ſhown in two parts of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>The pleaſures in ſufferings,</hi> and the <hi>ſufferings in pleaſures.</hi> This affectation in diſcourſe appears ſo childiſh, ſmells ſo much of the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Declamator, and ſo little of the gravity of the Pulpit, that it is pittied by every one who has the leaſt uſe of their reaſon; for in thoſe ſtudied oppoſitions there is ſeldom any thing that is ſolid; though ſometime poſſibly they may be witty, yet the parts are oftentimes comprehended the one in the other, when they are exactly diſcuſs'd: And this contains but one and the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:65667:70"/>ſame thing in effect, though they are two in appearance. Beſide, they often weaken the Subject by this too curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care to give it an agreeable variety, which would be more ſtrong if it were more natural.</p>
               <p>It is for the moſt part the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Preachers who ſeek after this fineneſs in the diviſion of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes. It was not the manner of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> nor thoſe great men of the Church; they found the moſt common diſtributions, as being moſt natural, alwayes the beſt; they had a noble contempt of the reputation of being witty in theſe kind of things, which only can ſucceed by being natural, by their ſimplicity, and by the ſtrength of the reaſons that recommend them.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:65667:71"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 22.</head>
               <p>Nothing ſo much contributed to the great ſucceſs the Apoſtles had in preaching the Goſpel, than their own practiſe of it; their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample was the beſt inſtruction, and their preachings were rendred more powerful by their humility, by their mortification, and by their poverty, than by their reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or Diſcourſe. And indeed the moſt effectual way of perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Chriſtianity, is by the Life and Manners of thoſe that preach. It was the Eloquence of Jeſus Chriſt, firſt to practiſe himſelf what he taught. He that preaches a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere morality, with a cheerful and vermilion countenance, will not eaſily perſwade to what he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts; for he gives cauſe to believe that he practiceth not what he teacheth, and his viſage deſtroyes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65667:71"/>his Reaſons. All the world hath ſeen the little ſucceſs of ſome, who could not by all the emotion of their zeal, make the leaſt impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe the rigour of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality had diminiſhed nothing from their thriving Carkaſes; for the Auditors oftentimes regard more his Countenance, than his Reaſons. The Countenance of the Preacher gives not a little conſolation to thoſe who cannot accommodate themſelves to that ſeverity, which theſe ſanguine Complexions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with ſo much zeal. I do not ſay but that the people whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings are dull, may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon; but the exteriour part cannot do it, for they judge according to appearance; and though the Preacher may ſpeak never ſo great a truth, if his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be ſuſpected, his Reaſons will be ſo alſo. It is ſomtimes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſpeak little, to perſwade
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:65667:72"/>much; for all appears falſe that a Preacher ſayes, if he have once the reputation of one that will amplifie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 23.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Impoſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo oratores viſi ſumus. <hi>Cic. in Brut.</hi>
                  </note>Every one is very well perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Reflection that I come to make, That the moſt ordinary Artifice of Preachers is to impoſe on their Auditors, and to make themſelves appear what they are not. The morality that they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe is ſo much the more ſevere, as that which they practiſe is ſweet and commodious; and becauſe in preaching the Goſpel he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily edifie his Auditors to maintain the dignity of his Miniſtry, he is conſtrained to take upon him at leaſt the appearances of ſeverity; whilſt the ſweetneſs of the life he leads, convinces us of the little diſpoſition he hath to a real Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:65667:72"/>But of all theſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Zelots, who would be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the ſeverity of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals they deliver, the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſort are thoſe ſhallow and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Devot's, who preach to the people Chimerical Devotions, and their own Fantaſtick Viſions, who without diſtinguiſhing what is eſſential from what is not, they bring all things to the laſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I know ſome that have this Art to impoſe, without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing of fineneſs or ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by a ſtrong natural imagination, which is fed by the little Light they receive from the reading of the Goſpel: So that it is not the Spirit that is alwayes Maſter; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns it ſelf up to the conduct of the Imagination; and as oft as that is tranſported, all that the Spirit ſaith by its impreſſion, is ſo alſo. A Preacher muſt avoyd this with a particular care, or elſe he will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65667:73"/>make very ſtrange diſorders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, but eſpecially amongſt the Women, who are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally feeble and ignorant; for the more extravagant a Preacher is, and the more extraordinary his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, by ſo much he is rendred more capable to make the greater diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance: This diſorder is but too frequent in this Age, as well as in that of the falſe Devot's whoſe vertues were all counterfeit, which hath given occaſion to decry ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much that devotion, whereby they have made at preſent in the world a ſpecies of Intrigue, and a manner of profeſſion to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh't from others. But they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be very devout, who ſeek only to diſtinguiſh themſelves by a bare profeſſion, that they make to be ſo.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:65667:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 24.</head>
               <p>How many Preachers are there, who by the vehemence of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſeem to throw ſtones at the heads of their Auditors, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them to amend their faults, and ſcarce ever think of preaching thoſe to which themſelves are ſubject? They ſtudy the Fathers Divinity and Rhetorick, and all things elſe that may contribute to render them renowned. In fine, they ſtudy all things, but the knowledge of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Their ill pronunciation, their minds, their grimaces, their action, their geſtures ſo little conformable to a true decorum, and whatſoever elſe that is violent in their perſons and outward behaviour, to ſuffer to ſtick to them, they, without any care of Reformation, by this negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their perſons: they corrupt oftentimes their beſt natural quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:65667:74"/>which poſſibly might contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to render them more ſucceſsful and profitable, if they would give themſelves the trouble to think on it: For how can they ſo much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this, without making it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that they yet more neglect their Auditors? what reſpect can we have for what they ſay, when we have no difference for their perſons. We have ſeen not long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, a Preacher of this kind, who could not put off his air of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, whereby he corruped his other talents, becauſe he would not take the pains to amend it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 25.</head>
               <p>A Chriſtian Preacher ought to ſhun nothing ſo carefully as that which is too gliſtring, either in words or thoughts; he muſt know how to ſpeak in a ſtile poliſh't with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affectation. All that is ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65667:74"/>and artificial is falſe, and little agreeable to the eloquence of the Pulpit; his diſcourſe ought to be ſimple, reaſonable, and natural, to which the commerce with the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian and Spaniſh Simoniſts, is very contrary. This reading of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns does but amuſe him, becauſe he knows not the Antients; and he frames to himſelf a falſe Idea of that Eloquence, whoſe true Character is very much oppoſed to what is ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, dazeling and witty. The true Eloquence of the Pulpit ought not to endeavour to ſuſtain it ſelf but by the greatneſs of the Subjects of which it treats, by its ſimplicity, and by its reaſons: He does but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it, who pretends to adorn it with the Riches of the Pagans. The Preacher ought to baniſh from the Pulpit all Citations of prophane Authors, all reflections upon their Maximes, and all their ſtories, as unworthy of ſo ſacred a Subject.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65667:75"/>The holy Scripture is rich enough to furniſh him with Ornaments of all kinds which are of uſe to this Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; when he has well medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, he will find plenty of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Examples to ſtrengthen and eſtabliſh his diſcourſe; all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authorities ought to have no place in the Pulpit, as too eſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and too little conformable to the Sanctity of his Character. A Preacher, which ought not to put in uſuage any thing, but what is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ought to be extreamly ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in ſerving himſelf with any thing that is not ſo: He muſt alſo fly the affectation of making the entrance of his diſcourſe too gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring, whoſe fair thoughts ſurprize and dazle the ſpirits of their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, but are very far from having that junction which accompanies the Word of God, reducing it to a dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which renders it ſterile, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:65667:75"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 26.</head>
               <p>Finally, the moſt eſſential cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of this Eloquence, which we likewiſe ſo miſerably neglect, is the Art to allot divers dayes to the ſame thoughts, which is done by varying them after different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; for that the common people, which uſually makes the greater number, whereof every Audience is compoſs'd, wants prompt and eaſie conceptions: So that it is to great purpoſe (if the Preacher would have them reap any fruit or profit) that he propoſe the truth of the Goſpel in ſuch a manner as may inſinuate little by little into their ſpirits, and to diſpoſe in order their impreſſions upon their hearts and reſolutions; which cannot be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but by thoſe variations that he muſt give to the ſame propoſition, to imprint them more deep in the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65667:76"/>ſpirits of his Hearers, inſinuating by frequent repetitions the ſame things under different forms of ſpeech. It was thus that St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> preach't in the firſt Ages of the Church, and the famous <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nade</hi> in this laſt Age: Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h which have been the moſt perfect models that can be propoſed to a Preacher. A diſcourſe (to anſwer this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter) muſt not be over-charg'd with matter, leſt it too much oppreſs the Auditor. That rapid Eloquence, which ſo much pleaſes the leſſer wits, and is only recommendable for its impetuoſity and tranſport, is not at all proper for the people, who have neither ſo much penetration of ſpirit, or promptitude to keep pace with it, and retain its fruit. I cannot forbear to note, that ſome Preachers owe all their ſucceſs to the weakneſs and ignorance of the Auditors; but that ſucceſs ought not to authorize an evil cuſtom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:65667:76"/>that it happens only from the little reaſon and ſtupidity of thoſe to whom they ſpeak.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>§. 27.</head>
               <p>The choice of matters we ought to treat of in the Pulpit, is of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter importance than we commonly think it is. We ſeldom conſider the great Importance in the choice of matters which ought to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in the Pulpit: They fall into an ill cuſtom, who upon that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, preach only what others have done before: The choiceſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers know how to diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the indifferent; in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it is one of the eſſential talents of great Genius's to make choice of great Subjects in all the matters that they treat of, to which they know how to add that natural variety that it ought to have: For as every
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:65667:77"/>Subject is only great ſo far as it is ſolid: All that paſſes the teſt of a Preacher, who hath a great and firm Judgment, becomes proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably ſolid, and whatſoever is ſo, is alwayes proper to preach. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this talent is rare, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preachers are much wanting in the choice of worthy Subjects, I have thought it not unprofitable to propoſe ſome of them, that may be the moſt proper to this Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the Pulpit.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Greatneſs and Majeſty of God, as it is deſcribed in the Prophets, and in other places of Scripture. To give an Idea of him to the greateſt part of Chriſtians, who know ſo little of him, the Preacher muſt render him terrible to the wicked, and amiable to the good; and ſo (by making him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſuch as he is) they both may be equally edified.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:65667:77"/>
               <p n="2">2. The truth of our Religion, which has been atteſted by the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt men of the world, and thoſe which were moſt exempted form Intereſt or Paſſion, and has never been conteſted but by thoſe whoſe ſentiments were corrupted by the contagion of their manners.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The neceſſity and importance of Salvation, and the difficulty to attain to it, by reaſon of the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of death, which oftentimes ſurprizes us in our diſobedience.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The greatneſs of the act of Redemption, and the unſpeakable bounties of our Saviour, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments and thanks that we owe to him, and which he hath merited of us by his Sufferings, and by the effuſion of his Blood.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The unprofitableneſs of the life of moſt part of Chriſtians, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the rich, who do ſo little to gain Heaven; which being propoſed only as a conqueſt, cannot be gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:65667:78"/>by ſloth and ſoftneſs of life, as is that of Courtiers and Ladies.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The terrible account that he muſt render to God of his miſpent life, and the uſe of thoſe graces that he beſtowed on him, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives from death his laſt arreſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Sanctity of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Religion, as that of the Reſurrection, which is the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of our Faith: the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the motive of our Hope, by the aſſurance of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator with God; the deſcent of the Holy Spirit, which is the ground of our Charity, and the love we owe to God, by a bond ſo holy.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The greatneſs and dignity of the name of Chriſtian, which we receive at our Baptiſm; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the honour we have to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Children of God by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and in the right to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Kingdom of Heaven: This
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:65667:78"/>right, and that honour is a thing ſo glorious, that we cannot given an Idea great enough to a Chriſtian, nor make him well comprehend the obligation that ſuch a name layes upon him, to lead his life an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably in all purity and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The frequent Elogy of our Faith, which only can calm the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes, and the eternal Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of curioſity, to which the ſpirit of man is ſubject, and which is capable to ſweeten the perpetual troubles of this life, by giving us a clear proſpect of the Recompences which we hope for, <hi>fide ſperanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſubſtantia verum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. The holy uſe that we ought to make of the Sacraments, which are the moſt eſſential things in our Religion; he muſt ſhow in that uſage, what perfection the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Chriſtian (which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by our Baptiſm) doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:65667:79"/>us; he muſt make him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that penitence is a ſincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieges us to a true Repentance for our offences, and a firm reſolution to offend no more: He muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that the Euchariſt is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſacred nouriſhment of ſouls, but that it ought to be taken as a lively Image to refreſh in us the memory of that great act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which ought never to be effaced from the heart of a Chriſtian: That Marriage is not only a Chriſtian ſociety of man and woman, but alſo a means to ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians to acknowledg and honour God: And in this manner to explain all the Sacraments.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The ſufferings, humiliations, contradictions and poverty, which are the bleſſings of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the moſts certain pathes that lead to Heaven; as wealth and greatneſs are the greateſt obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:65667:79"/>
               <p n="12">12. To ſtir up in the faithful that ſpirit of fear and trembling, in which they muſt travel to their ſalvation, according to the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of the Apoſtle: It is good to proclaim in the eares of ſinners the terrour of the Judgments of God, to awaken them from that ſleepineſs into which their crimes have plunged them; and to raiſe a fear even in the better Chriſtians, by repreſenting the peril to which they expoſe themſelves, by negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the leaſt Graces which they receive from God, who ſeverely puniſheth the leaſt contempt or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployment of them.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The confidence in God which he muſt excite by frequent Diſcourſes upon his Providence, which we are not very apt to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, by reaſon of the ill ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitude we have got to impute all evenements to Chance, or to our own induſtry, without reflecting
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:65667:80"/>on what we are taught in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>that there falls not a hair of our Heads,</hi> that is to ſay, there arrives nothing in the world, how indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſoever it appears to our eyes, but by order of Providence, which we ought to acknowledg and adore in whatever comes to paſs, if we would render our Duty and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience compleat.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The obedience and perfect ſubmiſſion we owe to the Church, and the authority of its Deciſions; without which no ſociety can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; and becauſe it is the Rule of what we ought to believe, and of what we ought to practiſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we are alwayes expoſed to the mercy of our extravagant imaginations, and our changeable and unbridled deſires; and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which ought to be the moſt ſure and eſtabliſht thing in the World, becomes the moſt light and inconſtant.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:65667:80"/>
               <p n="15">15. The vertue of the Word of God, which converts ſinners, and humbles the wiſe of the World by the mouth of Babes and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The Panegyricks of the Saints, which they muſt propoſe to the Faithful as the true Models of that perfection which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of them according to their divers Conditions and Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Finally, the ſtrange miſery of the moſt part of Mankind, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of great men, who run after falſity and miſtake, and who oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy their minds in Chimera's and illuſions, whereof they ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to maintain the Maximes of their Libertiniſm.</p>
               <p>There are a great number of other Subjects of equal importance with theſe, as that eſſential Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Chriſtian, which is the Iove of our Neighbour, with an
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:65667:81"/>univerſal Charity, which doth not exclude our greateſt Enemies; the pardon of injuries; conformity to the Will of God in our adverſity; alms; the diſtruſt of our ſelves; the good uſe of our time, and a faithful employment of our Graces, penitence, humane reſpects, which are ſo contrary to the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, the horrour of ſin, the care of our ſalvation, the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence of God, fervency in his Service, prayer; and all things that are moſt capable to move the hearts, and contribute to the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the people, we muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things endeavour: He cannot too often propoſe to the people the innocence of manners, which the ſanctity of our Religion requires, which cannot eaſily be attained, but a by holy retreat, and a love of ſolitude. The commerce of the world, how holy ſo e're it be, infects the heart with a conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:65667:81"/>which will corrupt our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in ſpite of all our precaution. The purity of Chriſtian Religion is ſo great, that we cannot attain any perfection in it, but by a deſertion and holy ſeparation from the world, and from men. This is that which the great Martyr of <hi>Sieily</hi> Saint <hi>Agatha</hi> had ſo well learned, when ſhe bleſs'd God with all her heart, that he had taken from her the ſpirit and care of the world. (<hi>Qui tuliſti a me amorem ſeculi.</hi>) In effect there is no man ſo good as he that lives conceal'd; and the moſt ſecret way is the moſt ſecure to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at Heaven.</p>
               <p>It remains (to atchieve fully theſe Reflections) that I propoſe ſome Model (Thoſe who have good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural diſpoſition for this Eloquence, may frame themſelves.) To effect this, I have given two examples of the moſt perfect Preachers that I have known in this Age; though
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:65667:82"/>their accompliſhments may appear miraculous, yet thoſe who have heard them ſpeak, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that I have not repreſented them greater than they really were; and that thoſe whom I have deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed are not only Preachers in Idea, but ſuch as were ſo indeed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which I might be ſuſpected to impoſe and amplifie.</p>
               <p>The firſt had the greateſt natural diſpoſition for Eloquence that I have ſeen; his perſon was graceful, his viſage was very agreeable, he was grave and modeſt, and all his outward behaviour was very ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: his voice was not the moſt excellent, but very clear and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible, and I know not, ſo inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, as irreſiſtably ingaged the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. The qualities of his ſpirit were anſwerable; he had a great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netration and exquiſite underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a ſtrong reaſon, an eaſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, a fine imagination, and a
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:65667:82"/>judgment very ſolid; his learning conſiſted in a perfect knowledge of Divinity, which enabled him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide all matters clearly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ambiguity: To this he had joyned a perfect knowledge of the Fathers, of which he made uſe with ſo much happineſs and addreſs, that they ſeem'd to have been writ pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for him: But nothing contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted ſo much to the renown of his learning, as that admirable Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, wherein he was extreamly happy; he could make what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion he pleaſed upon his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, by a pleaſing variety he gave to every thing: His reaſons ſo mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſupported each other, that the laſt was alwayes more ſtrong than the firſt; and beſides, he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing falſe or ſophiſtical in his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, but all exceeding ſolid; the force of his diſcourſe increaſing by degrees, the nearer it approach'd to the end, ſtriking the ſpirit with more
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:65667:83"/>vigour at the concluſion, than at the beginning. Finally, his true talent was to enlighten fully the underſtanding, and to touch yet more ſenſibly the heart: all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was a marvelous illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the matters whereof he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and after he had caſt into the ſpirit the ſeed of the movements that he propoſed; by the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful power that he had, he ſet in an inſtant all the engines of the ſoul on work, by thoſe movements that he judg'd moſt capable to be touched, and inflamed the heart by all the heat and ardeur of the paſſions, whereof he perfectly knew the art by a peculiar Rhetorick that he had formed; they hearkned to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with pleaſure, becauſe it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into their minds by this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing artifice; and he never preach't ſo long, but his Auditors could have wiſhed his Sermon longer; and they never apprehended him near his
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:65667:83"/>concluſion without a very ſenſible Regret: For in thoſe moments that he took poſſeſſion of their hearts, he became abſolute maſter to do what he pleas'd; he had this Art in ſo eminent a degree, that I have known ſome Libertines, who could not reſolve to hear him, out of fear of being conſtrained to render themſelves to his reaſons; for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever heard, became without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, his captive: But nothing ſpoke ſo much to his advantage, as the profound ſilence of his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. When he had finiſhed his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, one might alwayes have ſeen them riſe from their ſeats with their countenances pale and disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured, with their eyes heavy and dejected, and to depart from the Church ſtrangely moved, and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, without ſaying a word, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the moſt touching Subjects; and when he took occaſion to ſpeak of what was terrible he ſhewed, that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:65667:84"/>he had the ſame reflections with that great Maſter of this Art, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter plus valet apud plurimus timor malorum, quam ſpes bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> The ſpirits of the people are leſs ſenſible to the hopes of good, than to the fear of evil: This made him alwayes ſay, that a Preacher ſhould generally preach terror, and this indeed was his chief Character; but as he ſometimes preached out of humour, to which the greateſt men are ſubject, he had in certain ſubjects ſuch a heavineſs of ſpirit as would not have without difficulty been underſtood, with out that touching and pathetick Air, which was his firſt talent.</p>
               <p>The other Preacher that I have known, had an equal natural diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and I dare ſay all the learning of the former, but he poſſeſs't it in a very different manner: I never ſaw more of Art in any Orator, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more diligence to conceal it; for under the appearance of a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:65667:84"/>and negligence, he cover'd the greateſt Art that ever was. This negligence was accompanied with ſo many graces, that alwayes charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe his Auditors were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by his manner of ſpeech, that he thought of nothing leſs. His ſoveraign Talent, was the ſecret that he had found to make it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that all his Art was natural, becauſe that it was couched under the moſt ſtudied negligence in the world, ſo that his Audience eaſily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned themſelves to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that they took in hearing him; they ſuffer'd themſelves to be lead without caution, or any reſiſtance; as his reaſons were ſtrong, and as he knew how to expoſe them with all their powers, they made extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and proportionable impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but his manner of delivering them was ſo pleaſing, that they could not underſtand them without being raviſhed: This was the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:65667:85"/>effect of that Eloquence which was leſs in the words and things, than in the manner of ordering and ſpeaking them: And as he had an Art to pleaſe in all that he ſaid, and that when he ſpoke he ſeem'd ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with the graces which he had delivered; he became ſoveraignly Eloquent, for thereby he never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of perſwading; he knew how to mix the force of his reaſons with Authority, and with a temper which adorned all that he ſaid, inſomuch that he led the ſpirit of his Auditors in Triumph which way he pleaſed, becauſe they could not defend themſelves from the pleaſure by which he ſurprized them: All his Morals were correct, becauſe his reaſon was ſo; the Subjects that he treated of were alwayes rendred great by the importance of thoſe Truths whereof they were compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; he had nothing falſe in his thoughts, nor ſuperfluous in his
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:65667:85"/>words; and when he made any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, he alwayes returned to his Subject with all imaginable facility, and without the leaſt maim in the ſenſe or connexion. By theſe agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wayes he went more directly to the heart, than the other, who fetched a larger circuit, making his way firſt through the Spirit: One was indeed more moved and ſtruck by the force and vehemence of the former; but more charmed, pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated, and ſurprized by the graces and agreements of the ſecond. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, both the one and the other were fully accompliſhed in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter that they aſſumed, and in that Eloquence which they had formed to themſelves. A Preacher ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as theſe were, whoſe Images I have drawn, is one of the greateſt gifts that God can beſtow on his Church, becauſe it is a means to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie whole Provinces and Realms, by reforming the Licentious, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:65667:86"/>the irregularity of manners which reigns amongſt the People. This is that ſacred leaven, which God by the care of his Providence hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to all the corruptions which have courſe in the world. So that I believe the few good Preachers that we find in theſe dayes proceeds from the little care they take to ask of God theſe kind of Graces, which cannot be ſought with too much paſſion. Let us then pour out our tears at his holy Altars with a Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith, with ardent Vows, and with a long perſeverance. Let us alwayes make to God that Prayer that he commended to his Apoſtles, which after their example we are bound to practice.</p>
               <p>Meſſis quidem multa operarii vero paucirogate; ergo Dominum Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ut mittat operarios in meſſem ſuam, <hi>Luke cap. 10.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:65667:86"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus I have finiſh'd theſe few Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections. I have choſen this Method, that I might not ſeem to ſpeak like a Maſter of a Science which is no leſs univerſal than delicate: I might be juſtly accuſed of preſumption, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to give my Opinions as Rules from my ſelf; on the contrary, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have drawn ſome of them from the writings of the beſt Oraors, and ſome I may modeſtly challenge as the reſult of my own obſervation upon the little conformity I have found amongſt the Orators of this Age, to thoſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Precepts of</hi> Demoſthenes, Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>and</hi> Quintilian; <hi>whom if I have not cited ſo often as I approved their Opinions, it is not that I would have attributed to my ſelf any part of the glory that is their due, but to avoid breaking the thred of my Diſcourſe by too frequent Citations. The death of the moſt excellent Mr.</hi> Cowly <hi>is very much to be lamented, which with that of his Life, gave an unhappy peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:65667:87"/>to the deſign he had conceived to give us the pattern of ſeveral Stiles fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſeveral Subjects: His example might have put ſome bounds to that Poetick rage, from whoſe invaſion our holy places have not eſcaped: Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly none knew better than he, how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly to confine that Wanton: And in this it may be truly affirmed, he hath lefvery few ſucceſſors. The Stiles of our moſt witty men, ſeem the dictates of the ſame ſpirit which inſpires them in their raptures. Though our Common Laws allow but very little place to this Art, yet methinks the deſire of glory ſhould inflame them; and the care to ſupport the Majeſty of our Law, and the Dignity of its Profeſſors, ſhould ingage the Students to lay out ſome time in the acquiſition of this Art, and thoſe gentler Sciences that compleat an Orotar. But ſo far are they now from it, that when they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon that Study, they think it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to bid adien to all thoſe Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:65667:87"/>which teach Humanity, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and ſweetens Converſation. How miſerable a thing is it, and how ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to hear in common diſcourſe</hi> Plato <hi>and</hi> Cicero <hi>cited out of</hi> Cook <hi>and</hi> Plowden; <hi>as if the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Greek and Roman wiſdom were to be found couched in thoſe mangled fragments. I know not why it ſhould be inconſiſtent in a well formed and tempered mind to mix theſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Studies with thoſe which are more ſevere; this I am ſure would add to the honour of our Laws, the want of which renders them deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſpiſed. For though our Law deſerves thoſe juſt commendations, by which it is prefer'd to all the Laws of the world, yet</hi> lex eſt mutus Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus, <hi>ſaith</hi> Cicero, <hi>the Law of it ſelf is dumb, and ſpeaks not, but by the tongue of a learned and eloquent Lawyer. Much might be ſaid in commendation of our Language, which poſſibly equals the most ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:65667:88"/>in</hi> Europe <hi>in the plenty of ſoft, grave and majeſtick expreſſions, fit for all arguments: But ſince it is a Subject fit for another Diſcourſe, I omit further enlarging upon it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65667:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
